OpenAI 里 90% 的人都在用 Codex，不是 90% 的工程师。
90% of people at OpenAI use Codex, not 90% of engineers.
是整个公司 90% 的人。
That's 90% of the entire company.
对。
Yeah.
你前几天发的那条推文里说
This tweet the other day where you said
你想把 Codex 做成有史以来最好的桌面应用。
that you intend to make Codex the best desktop app that has ever existed.
对，Codex 的质量标准必须非常高，高到你几乎不会
Yeah, the quality bar for Codex had to be so high that there was never, like,
在打开它做下一件事时有任何犹豫，
a hesitation that you have opening this app to do the next thing,
它就是你自然而然的选择，
that this was your natural choice,
就像人们习惯了打开一个浏览器标签页，对吧？确实是这样。我知道。
just like people have kind of come to open a browser tab, right? That's true. I know.
一直有数据出来，说你们在使用量上不断创下新纪录。
There's numbers constantly coming out about the records you guys are setting for usage.
我说不好，走着看吧。很多人好像挺喜欢这个应用。
I don't know. Like we'll see. A lot of people seem to like the app.
你觉得为什么 AI 和顶尖前沿模型就是不擅长设计？
Why do you think AI and the top frontier models are just not good at design?
我觉得设计比较难打分，
I think design's a little bit harder to grade
因为品位里的人性因素是你需要的反馈机制的一部分。
because the human aspect of taste is like part of the feedback mechanism you need.
用现在的技术还有点够不着，
That is still feeling a little bit out of reach with the current technology,
现在的产品团队形态跟几年前相比是什么样？
what is the shape of product team look like now versus couple years ago?
OpenAI 的每个人都很有主动性，点子也很多，
Everybody at OpenAI is very agentic, has great ideas,
所以大家什么都在做。
and so everybody's building everything.
并不是说大家在做根本不同的角色，或者去关注
And it's not that people are doing fundamentally different roles or focusing on
不同的事情。
different things.
而是整个反过来了。实现其实已经不是最贵的那部分了。
It's that it's backwards. The implementation is actually not the expensive part anymore.
而是，我敢说，品位。
It's, dare I say, taste.
你觉得会有这样一种坍缩到来，每个人什么都做，
You feel like there's this collapse coming where everyone's everything and
这就是未来吗？
that's just the future?
还是说你觉得我们还是会像现在这样大体分工？
Or do you think we're gonna continue to be mostly divided up?
有些事情是我担心的。
There are some things that I'm afraid of.
我听过很多公司会说，
I've heard a lot of companies be like,
我们要取消产品这个角色，每个人都当构建者就行。
we're getting rid of the product role and everybody's just gonna be a builder.
结果会怎样呢，今天我的嘉宾是 Andrew Ambrosino，
And then what happens is today my guest is Andrew Ambrosino,
OpenAI Codex 应用的产品和工程负责人。
product and engineering lead for the Codex app at OpenAI.
Codex 正在迅速成为大家做产品时首选的应用，
Codex is quickly becoming people's go to app for building products
也用在非产品的工作上，比如整理电脑里的文件、
and also for non product work like organizing files in your computer,
起草文档、做数据分析、读邮件等等。
drafting documents, doing data analysis, reading your emails and a lot more.
如果你能看到这一期的最后，
If you stick around for the end of this episode,
我们其实有一小段是在停止录制之后拍的，
we actually have a little clip from after we stopped recording
那时房间里的制作人开始聊他在剪辑工作中怎么用 Codex。
where the producer in the room started talking about how he uses Codex in his editing work.
从今年一月以来，Codex 的使用量增长了 6 倍。
Since this January, Codex usage has grown 6x.
目前他们有超过 500 万的周活跃用户。
They currently have over 5 million weekly active users.
我猜这个数字很快就会过时。
I suspect this number is quickly going to be out of date.
在 OpenAI 内部，几乎 100% 的员工每周都用 Codex。
Internally at OpenAI, nearly 100% of their employees use Codex weekly.
而且不只是工程师。
And that is not just the engineers.
Andrew 从设计师做到工程师，又做到产品经理，现在在打造这个应用，
Andrew is a designer turned engineer turned product manager who is building the app
越来越多的人正用它来做自己的产品。
that more and more of the world is using to build their own products.
在正式开始前，别忘了去看看 Lenny 的 Productpass.com，可以免费用一年
Before we get into it, don't forget to check out Lenny's Productpass.com for a year
全世界最热门、做得最用心的 AI 产品，
free of the hottest and most well crafted AI products in the world,
仅对 Lenny newsletter 订阅者开放。那么，
available exclusively to Lenny's newsletter subscribers. With that,
有请 Andrew Ambrosino。
I bring you Andrew Ambrosino.
Andrew，非常感谢你来，欢迎来到播客。
Andrew, thank you so much for being here, and welcome to the podcast.
谢谢你邀请我。这是难得的一次线下面对面录制。
Thank you for having. This is a rare in person podcast.
我很少做这种事。
I rarely do this kind of thing.
看看效果吧。走着看。走着看。大家更喜欢这种。
We'll see how it goes. We'll see. We'll see. People like these more.
我们准备这次聊天的时候，我问过你，
When we were preparing for this chat, I asked you,
你最想让大家从这次对话里带走的是什么，
what's the biggest thing you want people to get out of this conversation,
你说是 AI 正在如何改变产品工作的形态。
and you said that it was how AI is changing the shape of product work.
你所在的可能是最前沿、最 AGI 上头的软件团队。
You're working at maybe the most bleeding edge AGI-pilled software team there is.
所以你有一个很有意思的视角，能看清事情要往哪走，
So you have a really interesting lens into where things are heading,
其他团队一两年或者更久之后会到哪个阶段，
where other teams are gonna be in a year or two or, or more,
现在的产品团队形态跟几年前相比是什么样？
what is the shape of product team look like now versus a couple years ago?
现在作为一个领导者，最难做的一件事，
One of the, the hardest things to do right now as a leader,
在打造这些产品时，在我看来就是整个流程的反转，
building these products is just sort of the inversion of the process in my mind,
我觉得很多人都聊过这个。
which I think a lot of people have talked about.
那就是任何人都能构建任何东西，对吧？
Which is that anybody can build anything, right?
我现在基本相信，从零开始，
Like I I generally believe now that starting from scratch,
只要你和这些模型对话，我们的、别人的都行，
if you talk to these models, ours, anybody else's really, um,
你想要什么功能都能做出来，对吧？
you can stand up whatever feature you want, right?
这不一定是软件里最难的部分，但这真的，
And that's not necessarily a hard part of software, but that's like,
这真的很酷。
that's really cool.
我觉得这就造出了一种环境，大家什么都在做，对吧？
And I think that has created an environment where people are making all of this, right?
你给大家无限的 token。
You give people unlimited tokens.
OpenAI 的每个人，OpenAI 很真实，大家都有好点子。
Everybody at OpenAI, OpenAI is is very authentic, has great ideas.
所以每个人都在构建各种东西。
And so everybody is building everything.
而我觉得，你回头看看产品流程，
Whereas I think, you know, you look back at product process
我们这么多年一直在跑的那套流程，其实有点，
that we've all run for a long time and it's been a little bit.
是相反的，对吧？它更像是先做研究、构思，
Opposite, right? It's been kind of research ideation.
也许会做点原型，但你懂的，
Maybe there was some prototyping, but it was, you know,
就算我们过了瀑布式那个阶段，
even when we got past waterfall,
那套思路里还是带着一种味道，就是实现很贵，
it was still kind of flavored of like the implementation is expensive and
所以你想做的就是提前把所有实现风险降下来，
so you what you want to do is you want to derisk all implementation upfront through
通过文档、通过研究。
documents, through research.
通过原型，因为原型
Through prototypes because prototypes
和设计更便宜，这大概就是当时的假设。
and designs are cheaper was kind of the the Assumption there.
而现在变了，彻底变了。
And that's changed. That's like totally changed.
现在我敢肯定，对于某个功能，有 90 种不同的探索，
And right now, I'm sure there are 90 different explorations for there's this feature
某个我们特别需要做的功能，我敢肯定有 90 个互不协调的
that we desperately need to do that I'm sure there are 90 different uncoordinated
团队在做、在试，对吧？
teams like implementing and trying, right?
所以简短的回答就是，
So I guess the short answer is like it's,
它是反过来的，并不是大家在做完全不同的角色，
it's backwards and it's not that people are doing fundamentally different roles or
或者关注不同的事，也不是技能组消失了，
focusing on different things or that even skill sets have vanished or
或者岗位角色就这么没了。
that roles have just disappeared.
而是它反过来了，对吧？
It's that it's backwards, right?
实现其实已经不再是那个贵的部分了。
The implementation is actually not the expensive part anymore.
我斗胆说一句，是品位，是那个筛选的过程。
It's, dare I say, taste, but it's the curation process.
就是说，在那 90 次尝试里，哪些是好的？
It's like, of those 90 attempts, like, what's good about these?
哪些该融进这个东西的其他方面，对吧？我们该怎么定位它？
What should we fold into other aspects of this, right? How should we frame this?
它该不该成为另一个功能的一部分？对吧？
Should it be part of this other feature? Right?
这个切换里该有几个分段？
How many segments should be in the toggle?
就是所有这些事。
Um, you know, all of those things.
本期节目由本季的呈现赞助商 WorkOS 支持。
This episode is brought to you by our season's presenting sponsor, WorkOS.
OpenAI、Anthropic、Cursor、Vercel、Replit、
What do OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, Vercel, Replit,
Sierra、Clay 以及数百家成功公司有什么共同点？
Sierra, Clay and hundreds of other winning companies all have in common,
它们都由 WorkOS 提供支持。
they are all powered by WorkOS.
如果你在做一款面向企业的产品，
If you're building a product for the enterprise,
你一定体会过集成单点登录、SCIM、RBAC、
you've felt the pain of integrating single sign on, SCIM, RBAC,
审计日志等大公司要求的功能有多痛苦。
audit logs and other features required by large companies.
WorkOS 把这些成交障碍变成即插即用的 API，配上现代化的开发者平台，
WorkOS turns those deal blockers into drop in APIs with a modern developer platform
专为 B2B SaaS 打造。
built specifically for B2B SaaS.
我投资的每一家初创公司，
Literally every startup that I'm an investor in
只要开始往高端市场扩张，最后都用上了 WorkOS。
that starts to expand up market ends up working with WorkOS.
那是因为它们就是最好的，
And that's because they are the best,
不管你是想拿下第一个企业客户的种子期创业公司，
whether you are a seed stage startup trying to land your first enterprise customer
还是正在全球扩张的独角兽，
or a unicorn expanding globally,
WorkOS 都是让你做好企业级准备、打通增长的最快路径。
WorkOS is the fastest path to becoming enterprise ready and unblocking growth.
它基本上就是企业级功能里的 Stripe。
It's essentially Stripe for enterprise features.
访问 WorkOS.com 开始使用，或者直接去他们的 Slack，
Visit WorkOS com to get started or just hit up their Slack
那里有真正的工程师等着回答你的问题。
where they have actual engineers waiting to answer your questions.
WorkOS 让你构建更快，配有好用的 API、
WorkOS allows you to build faster with delightful APIs,
完善的文档和顺畅的开发者体验。
comprehensive docs and a smooth developer experience.
现在就去 WorkOS.com，让你的应用做好企业级准备。
Go to WorkOS. Com to make your app enterprise ready today.
品位真是个热词，我想回头再聊这个。
Taste such a such a buzzword, I want to come back to that.
90 个原型这个说法，太有意思了。
This idea of 90 prototypes. So interesting.
我先确认一下我理解得对不对，现在流传着一种说法。
So just to make sure I understand that, so there's an idea out there floating around.
以前 OpenAI 的人做法是写文档。
OpenAI people used to do is write docs.
就是：我们要做什么，功能是什么，策略是什么。
Yeah, here's what we're gonna build, here's the feature, here's the strategies.
也就是 PRD。而你现在描述的做法，很有道理，
PRD today, what you're describing, which makes all the sense,
就是大家直接做一个原型。
is people just create a prototype
你的意思是，公司里不同的人都有类似的想法，
and what you're saying is people across the company have kind of similar ideas
现在不再是写一份文档。
and now instead of a doc.
他们各自做一个小原型，
They create their little prototype and
于是就有了差不多九十个不同的东西可以看，然后挑一个，
that leads to kind of 90 different things people can look at and maybe pick,
说这就是我们想走的方向。对，这种情况很多。嗯。
here's the direction we want to go down. Yeah, idea. There's a lot of this. Yeah. Um.
而且你知道，这不只是发生在我们这里。
And, you know, it's not just happening here.
你也看到很多产品负责人说 PRD 已死，原型才是王道。
Like you've seen many product leaders say PRDs are dead and prototypes are in.
但我其实完全不认同这个说法。
And I actually don't believe this at all.
我觉得现在正在发生的一件有意思的事是，
I think that one of the interesting things that is happening right now is
因为在每一种媒介上，实现的成本都变得这么低，
that because implementation has gotten so cheap across every medium,
大家很容易就直接跳到做原型，
it's very tempting to jump straight to a prototype,
尤其是如果你不是工程师，对吧？
especially if you're not an engineer, right?
尤其是如果你从来不会写代码、从来没兴趣，或者从来
Especially if you've never been able to write code or never been interested or never
没时间，那你很容易就想说，PRD 已死。
had the time, it's really tempting to say, like, PRDs are dead.
我直接给你看我想表达的东西。对吧。
Let me just show you what I mean. Right.
但我也注意到，对工程师来说，
What I've also noticed though, is that for engineers,
他们很容易写一大堆文档，
it's really tempting to write a lot of documents,
一大堆不值得读的文档。
a lot of documents that are not worth reading.
这不是在贬低写文档的人。
This is no shade on people writing documents.
而是当实现变得很廉价、很充足时，
It's that if implementation is abundant,
为你想表达的观点选对形式就变得很重要。
then it's really important to pick the right format for the point you're trying to make.
如果你要表达的是对一个模糊领域的产品清晰度，
If that point is product clarity around a vague area.
那它可能确实应该是一份文档。
Then it might actually be a document
但如果你想做的是把东西交到别人手里去试用，
if what you're trying to do is get something in people's hands to try out
去压力测试一种交互模式，
and to stress test an interaction pattern.
那它就是一个原型。
It's a prototype.
但我觉得现在有意思的一点就在于，
But I think, like, this is kind of the funny thing now, which is that, like,
选对媒介真的很重要。
it's really important to pick the medium.
有个播客嘉宾分享过一个词，你这么说时我就会想到它，
There's this term that a podcast guest shared that I think about when you say this,
就是叫做 primal mark（最初一笔）。
which is it's called the primal mark.
当一位设计师、画家或艺术家在画作上画下第一笔
When a designer or a painter or an artist just creates the first mark on a painting
或在一件作品上落下第一笔，
or a piece of art.
那一笔就成了你开始回应的对象。
That mark is what you start to respond to.
之后的一切都从你画的那第一笔延伸出来。
And so everything kind of trickles down from that first mark you make.
我听你的意思是，有时候原型是错误的第一步，
And what I'm hearing you saying is sometimes the prototype is the wrong first thing
因为那样你就只是在回应这个原型，而不是回应另一种想法，
to do because then you're just responding to this prototype versus a different idea
或者一个更大的想法。
versus a bigger idea.
所以我很喜欢听你这么说。不是说大家都觉得，好吧，算了，
So I love hearing this. So like everyone's just like, okay, forget it.
不再写东西、不再写文档、不再讲什么纯粹了，像你说的，
No more writing, no more docs, no more purity, as you're saying,
它们在特定场景下其实仍然有用。
they're actually still useful for specific use cases.
对，我还觉得，以前那个世界有一部分是，
Yeah, I think too, there's this part of the previous world was
媒介本身就隐含了很多信号，
that the medium implied it had baked in a lot of a lot of signal around
关于某个东西处在流程的哪个阶段，对吧？
where in the process something was, right?
所以如果你看到的东西看起来像是已上线的正式产品，
So if you're seeing something that feels like the app in production,
那就意味着它在流程后期，假设已经被降低了风险，
that means that it's late in the process, that assumptions have been derisked, that,
设计已经看过了，这是一个不错的业务目标，对吧？
you know, design has looked at this, that this is a good business goal, right?
而现在这些东西已经脱钩了。对。
And now those things are sort of divorced. Right.
之所以以前是那样，
And the reason it was that way is
是因为在一个东西真正降低风险之前，
because it was hard to get resources to build the thing
很难拿到资源去把它做出来。
until it was properly derisked.
而现在这一点基本已经不存在了，对吧？
And now that's like just out the window, right?
所以我觉得，我们要开始说：看，我们可以有原型，
And so I think it's really important to start saying, look, we can have prototypes,
也可以有文档。
we can have documents.
关键是，我们清不清楚这个东西是干嘛的，对吧？
Is it, are we clear around what this is doing, right?
因为正如你所说，你不想在这个东西上过度锚定。
Because to your point, you do not want to over anchor on this thing
它本来只是个探索，但现在看起来太像成品了，
that was meant to be an exploration, but now it looks so production ready that like,
哦，视觉上已经可以上线了。
oh, visually it's ready for prod.
但它其实并不能准确反映
But it's not actually the right model of,
研究的走向，或者用户真正想要的东西，
of where the research is going or what users are asking for,
也不一定符合业务需求，对吧？
what's right for the business, right?
不想过度强调品位这事，但又一次，
Not to overdo the taste thing, but it's like it's once again,
就是那种品位：知道该做什么、怎么呈现信息、
it's like the taste to know, like, what to work on, how to present that information,
怎么实现目标、用什么形式，这正在成为
like how to achieve the goals, what medium to use is emerging
最重要的事情。而这……
as like the most important thing to do. And that's.
这在每个领域都是如此。品位是什么？当你说好品位时，
It that's, that's in every field. What is taste? When you talk about good taste?
它是指你判断“这就是我们要投入的方向”，
Is it, is it what you describe deciding here's the thing we're going to invest in,
还是说当你做出东西后，判断“这对不对”，
is it also, once you have a thing, is this right?
“这是该发布的东西吗”？
Is this the thing to ship?
聊聊你怎么理解好品位、好判断，它到底
Talk about when you think about what is good taste, good judgment, what is,
具体是什么？
what is that concretely?
因为人们一听这词就说，对啊，我有好品位，我懂。
Because people hear this word, they're like, yeah, I have good taste. I know it.
那它在实践中到底是什么样？对。
What does it look like in practice? Yeah.
嗯，挺有意思。有条推文。对，我太上网了。
Um, it's funny. There was a tweet. Yeah, I'm too online.
有条推文，我想是昨天，来自 Linear 的产品负责人。
There were, there was a tweet, I think it was yesterday from the head of product at Linear.
我可能记错了。
I might be getting that wrong.
抱歉记错的话，他说人们过度强调品位里
Sorry to anybody who said people overemphasize the aesthetic part of what taste
审美的那部分，还用 Paul Graham 举例，
means and they used, um, Paul Graham, but they used him as an example,
说 Paul Graham 显然很有品位，但穿工装短裤。
saying Paul Graham clearly has great taste and wears cargo shorts.
对吧。所以我们得，我们得，
Right. Like, you know, we gotta, we gotta, like,
把品位到底是什么稍微理清楚。
tease out what taste means a little bit.
嗯，这里面有很多微妙之处。
Um, and, and there's a lot of nuance here.
我觉得你说的那些都算，全都包括在内。
I think it's all of the above to, to what you mentioned.
它确实有审美的成分，但也有
It's, it's the like there is an aesthetic part to it, um, but there's also a,
系统思维的成分，比如这在整个系统里怎么放？
a systems thinking part of it, like how does this fit in the system?
还有，我们要去哪、怎么去，这属于什么主题？
There is a, where are we going and how, like what, what theme is this part of?
还有怎么呈现。很多都是更大的上下文。
There's how to present this. A lot of it is wider context.
当然，品位里也有一些是，嘿，
And, you know, obviously there are parts of taste that are like, hey,
这个交互动画和它该表达的含义不匹配，对吧？
this interaction animation doesn't fit in the semantic meaning it's supposed to, right?
比如相对它想传达的东西，动作太干脆了。
Like, it's too snappy for what it's actually trying to convey.
这非常重要。
And that's incredibly important.
我可能在这方面关注得太多了。
And I focus probably too much on that.
嗯，但还有一层是，这东西
Um, but there's, there's like the, the, like, what should,
如果我们什么都能做，它到底该是什么样？
what should this be like if we can build anything?
目标是什么，我们怎么达到？
Like what's, what's the goal here and how do we get there?
我觉得这才是真正的品位问题。
That I think is actually the real taste question here.
每次听到这些，我都会想，
When I hear things like this, I always wonder,
随着 AI 越来越强、越来越好、承担越来越多的工作，
where will human brains continue to be valuable as AI becomes stronger and better
人的大脑在哪里还会持续有价值？
and doing more of the work?
感觉品位是其中一部分，
And it feels like taste is a part of it,
我沿着这个思路想到的是，AI 在实际设计上还是很差。
something I think about along these lines is just AI is still very bad at actual design.
AI 的产出并不出色。对，很少会是那种，就是它了。
Like the output of AI is not great. Yeah, rarely is it. Like, this is it.
完美搞定。对。总是那种，哦，这是 Claude 的设计，
They nailed it. Yeah. And it's always like, oh, this is Claude Design,
这是 Codex 的设计。
this is Codex design.
你觉得为什么如今的 AI 和顶尖前沿模型就是不擅长设计？
Why do you think AI and the top frontier models are just not good at design today?
对。你觉得它们能做到吗？
Yeah. And do you think they'll get there?
你觉得我们会走到那种，天哪，搞定了的地步吗？
Do you think we'll get to a place of like, holy moly, we're done?
对，我倾向于认为它落后有一些现实原因，
Yeah, I tend to think that there are some practical reasons why it's lagged
也有一些更难攻克的问题。
and also some harder problems to crack.
我不在我们的研究部门，说这些肯定会被骂。
I'm not in our research org, like, I'm sure I'll get yelled at for saying this.
我觉得设计比软件更难打分，你懂的，
I think design's a little bit harder to grade than software and that, you know,
建立一个能训练模型、判断什么是好设计、
creating a loop where you can train the model and like what's good design
什么是坏设计的循环，比起判断
and what's bad design is just a little bit more tedious and onerous than, you know,
代码能不能编译要更繁琐、更麻烦。
does the code compile? Does it.
代码能不能按预期运行，因为品位里人的那一面，
You know, do, do what it's supposed to right it because the human aspect of taste is,
正是你需要的反馈机制的一部分。
is like part of the feedback mechanism you need.
我还觉得，各家实验室以往都会投入去让自己的模型擅长
I also think that, uh, the labs historically invest in making their models good at
那些能加速 AI 研究的事情，而在那个时代
things that accelerates AI research and and that in the era,
编程模型的早期阶段，很明显模型能够
the early era of coding models is very clear that the model being able to,
写出正确的代码就会加速研究，对吧？这一点是
to write correct code would accelerate research, right? In a way that you.
在设计上很难同样成立的
Can't really make the same case for design,
不是说擅长设计不重要，而是它不直接处在那个
not that getting good at design isn't important, it's that it's not directly in that,
飞轮里，对吧？这些是很现实的原因，而且我，你懂的
that flywheel, right? Um, those are practical reasons and I, you know.
这些会消失。这些模型会在设计上变得相当不错
Those will go away. Like these models will get pretty good at design.
但有一些更模糊的东西，会非常难搞定
There are some kind of murkier things that is, is gonna be really tough.
我大概列了一个简短的清单
Um, like I have kind of a short list of them.
其一是，什么算是好设计里有一层文化的成分
One is there is an aspect of of culture to what is considered good design in
你还记得吧，大概是去年
that you remember it was probably what, last year where like,
每一个新出的网站基本都是在抄 Linear 的网站，对吧？
every new website that came out was just a copy of Linear's website, right?
比如 Linear 的网站，设计很棒，品位很好
Like, Linear's website, great design, great taste.
如果一个模型能做到那样，我会觉得，哇，这是巨大的飞跃，对吧？
Like, if a model did that, I'd be like, wow, this is an incredible leaps here, right?
但如果我有个模型每次都输出 Linear 的网站
If I have a model that outputs Linear's website every time,
那不是这里的挑战，对吧？
that's not the challenge here, right?
有一定程度的新颖性
Um, there's an amount of like novelty
在设计里比在软件工程里更重要
that is more important in design than it actually is in software engineering.
比如软件工程，你几乎
Like software engineering, you almost,
你会希望它更偏向已知的模式，对吧？
you must want it to over index unknown patterns, right?
而设计则是，不，这里有一种随机性
Whereas design, it's like, no, there's an element of randomness here and,
和新颖性，对吧？
and novelty, right?
还有，对我来说，我花了很多时间写代码
There's also the, you know, to me, like I spent a lot of time writing code or,
或者说在早期的 Codex 上监督代码
you know, supervising code on the early Codex out.
而即使模型在设计上变强了，还是有一种
And even as the models get good at design, there's sort of a.
抽象层，是软件设计
An abstraction layer that is an interplay between the software design
和正在写的代码之间的相互作用
and the code that's being written,
比如这个角落里的这个东西应该和
like this thing over here in this corner should share X, y,
下面这个东西在代码库里共享 X、Y、Z，对吧？
and Z in the code base with this thing down here, right?
这和说模型需要成为一个更好的
And that's a little bit different than saying the model needs to be a better
设计师有点不一样，尤其是在，那种不是视觉的层面
designer, especially on the, like, you know, that's not visual.
那算是视觉设计，但要深得多
That is visual design, but it is significantly deeper.
它关乎其中的抽象
It's about the abstractions in that.
比如，如果明天我们公司做品牌重塑
Like, oh, if tomorrow our company did a rebrand,
浅层的做法就是我们得
the shallow version of this is that we have to, you know,
一个一个地更新 263 个组件
update 263 components one by one.
深层的做法是，看起来不同的这两个东西之间的语义
The deep version is like the semantics between these two things that look different,
比如它们都在列表里，用这种样式来向用户传达这种交互
like they're both in list that have the like this style to convey this interaction
模式
pattern to the user.
我觉得，用现在的技术，这一点仍然感觉有点够不着
And I think, like, that is still feeling a little bit out of reach with the current
对吧，那个抽象层
technology, right, that abstraction layer.
所以我觉得，随着我们走过这个过程，对吧
So I think, you know, as, as we've gone through this process, right, of, you know,
我们十一月开始做 Codex 应用，那时还没全天用它
we started the Codex app in November and we weren't using it full time.
现在我们什么都用它
Now we use it for everything.
这是一段历程，但现在我们用它时实际做的事
That's been a journey, but now it's like the things that we actually do
已经是不一样的事情了
while using it are different things.
所以问题是什么来着？我知道那是个很精彩的回答
So what was the question? I know that was, that was an amazing answer.
说到设计和创造力，Codex 应用刚出来时
Uh, speaking of design and being creative, the Codex app, when it came out,
是一个很新的东西
it's like such a new thing.
对，之前没人见过的东西
Yeah. That nobody has had seen before.
它不是终端那种，也不是 IDE 那种，而是这样一个聊天
It's like not a terminal thing. It's not an ID thing. It's like this chat,
一个会写代码的东西
a thing that codes.
而且你能看到代码
And you could see code.
对，就像你说的，感觉 AI 很难说
Yeah, to your point, it feels like it'd be hard for AI to be like,
这是一套全新的编程范式
here's a whole new paradigm for how to code.
而这感觉就是人脑目前仍然有价值的地方，就像
And that feels like where human brains continue to be valuable for now is like
几乎是创造力，是想出新东西，而不是那些
creativity almost and coming up with something new versus like patterns of things
已经被做过的模式
that have been done before.
对，我完全同意。目前先为人脑鼓个掌吧
Yeah, I mean, I totally agree. Let's give it up for the human brain for now.
我们在准备这期节目的时候，
As we were getting ready for this,
你说你听了跟 Jenny 那期，
you said that you were listening to the episode with Jenny,
她是 Claude Code、cowork 之类产品的设计负责人。
who is the head of design for Claude Code and cowork and such.
她有一整套观点，认为设计流程已经死了。
And she had this whole kind of thesis that the design process is dead.
没时间做设计了，一切变化太快。
There's no time for design. Things are moving too fast.
现在就直接开干，设计只是在过程中做些引导和把控。
Just build now. And design is kind of steering things as things move along.
你的意思是，你对设计流程有点不一样的看法。
You're implying you have kind of a different perspective on the design process.
其实在很多点上，我和 Jenny 应该是一致的。
We probably agree on a lot of this, Jenny and I.
我本来就不太喜欢设计流程，尤其是那套正规的设计流程。
I wasn't a fan of the design, like the design process proper.
我认同她说的，它确实已经死了。
I agree with her take that it is, it is dead.
而且在 AI 出现之前，我就真的不喜欢这套流程。
And I genuinely was not a fan of this process before AI.
我快速说一下这个流程，让大家想象一下所谓的设计。
Like I describe the process real quick just from people think about the design.
对对，所以我是说，我……
Yeah, yeah, so I mean, I.
几年前我做创业公司的时候，我们会，你懂的，
When I ran a startup a number of years ago, we, we would, you know,
招设计师，当时有一篇挺挖苦的文章，
do design hiring and there was this sort of snarky article
讲的是所谓的“案例研究工厂”，
that came out about like the case study factory and it was,
大概是 SERP 那个中期时代的东西，对吧？
it was like mid serp era stuff, right?
意思是设计师被灌输这套流程，并且把它
And it was that designers are being taught about this process and valuing
看得高于一切，甚至高于所有结果，对吧？
that above all else, above all outcomes even, right?
而只要某个东西走完了这套流程，就意味着两件事。
And if something went through this process, that two things were true.
第一，它会很好，流程能保证质量、保证效果。
One, it would be good and the process would guarantee quality and guarantee impact.
第二，只要东西走完了这个流程，它就算是好的，
And also that if something, the thing was good if it went through that process,
哪怕你不喜欢、没人用，也无所谓，就是那套流程，
even if you don't like it and nobody uses it and it's like the process with,
你懂的，用户研究、发散、再收敛那一套。
you know, of of user research and the divergence and the convergence.
它是个正确的框架，只是一直……
It's the right framework. It was always.
有点学院派，但我觉得现在真的暴露出一些
A little academic, but I think this is really exposing some areas
它站不住脚的地方，尤其是因为实现速度太快了。
where it falls down, especially because of the speed of implementation.
再说一次，那套流程其实建立在一个假设上，
And once again, that process is sort of predicated on the assumption
就是实现成本很高，你基本只能负担得起做一次。
that implementation is expensive and that you can really only afford to build once.
所以你需要彻底地，
And so you need to fully, like,
在动手实现之前，把问题空间和解决方案空间穷尽一遍，对吧？
exhaustively go through the problem space and the solution space before implementing, right?
然后我们也看到，比如像
And that you, and then like kind of we saw with like, you know,
Figma、Origami 这些工具，
Figma and origami and all of these tools
你可以把交互原型更早地拉进流程里，
that you can fast forward some of the insights by pulling interactive prototypes
从而提前得到一些洞见，对吧？
earlier into the process, right?
你可以模拟出接近成品的效果。
That you can, you know, simulate production.
后来就出现了一个梗，说高管们会
And like, you know, there ended up being sort of a meme about executives just being,
直接问：我们能不能就做个原型，然后指望它能直接上线？
like, well, can we just do a prototype and then, like, expect it to, you know, work?
但是，这件事是真实发生的，对吧？它变成了
But. But this thing was real, right? That this became part of the,
正规设计流程的一部分，对吧？
the design process proper, right?
我们把做原型也拉进了这个流程。
We pulled prototyping into that.
现在的问题是，你可以把整个实现都拉进这个流程里。
The problem now is that you can pull all of the implementation into that.
我觉得这就和很多旧假设产生了错位。
And there's a mismatch between, I think, a lot of assumptions.
还是那句话，你看到一个打磨得很完整的原型，
Again, like you see this fully polished prototype
看起来就像随时能发布，公司里有不少人看到
that looks like it's ready to go out the door and enough people at a company see
就会说，我们能不能……
that and they're like, can we?
我们能不能现在就发布这个？
Can we release this now?
但真实情况是，我们其实还处在设计流程的早期阶段，
But the appropriate like we're actually in the early design process stage
只是没人直接说出来，对吧？
and nobody's just saying that, right?
我们现在就处在这种一堆人一起探索的阶段，对吧？
Like this is this is where we are with like a bunch of like multiplayer exploration, right?
你知道，会有 90 个人有这个想法，它看起来很精致，但其实，
You know, 90 people will have this idea. It'll look really polished, but it's like,
不，这其实就是……
no, this is actually that.
这就是现在的设计流程，对吧？把设计流程和媒介、载体绑在一起，
That's the design process now, right? Tying the design process to mediums, media, uh,
这才是可怕的地方。
like that's the scary part.
现在的情况是，设计师有更多工具来做这个流程，对吧？
It's that designers have more tools now to do this process with, right?
你可以把东西直接放进现有产品里做 A/B 测试，或者就
You can put stuff into the current product and you can AB test it or just, you know,
把它当成一个原型。
use that as a prototype.
嗯，现在很多公司都有这种“产品迷你版”的概念，
Um, many companies right now have this idea of like a baby version of the product,
比如 Baby Cursor。
like Baby Cursor.
你在 Twitter 上见过，就像我们有 Baby Codex，对吧？
You've seen this on Twitter. Like we have Baby Codex, right?
一个极度简化的代码库
A dramatically simplified code base
它近似还原了正式应用里的所有交互
that approximates all of the interactions of the production app
所以在上面做 vibe coding 会快很多，对吧？
and therefore is a lot quicker to vibe code over, right?
因为你可以想，要是侧边栏这样工作会怎样？
Cause you can be like, well, what if the sidebar worked like this?
或者要是弹出一个面板，这里放一个群聊会怎样？
Or what if a pane came in and had, like, a group chat here?
要是怎样怎样，对吧？这是设计流程里一个很强大的工具。
What if XYZ, right? That's like a huge tool that's part of the design process.
所以说设计流程已死，我觉得既对也不对，对吧？
So to say that the design process is dead, I feel like it's both true and false, right?
就是说，如果你被工具绑住了，被那些
It's that if you are if you are tied to the tools and the, like the,
流程里具体到每天的细节绑住了，那确实
the exact like day to day specifics of the process, then yeah,
它是死了，你会过得很难受
it's dead like you're not gonna have a good time
但要把整个流程扔掉，或者把流程的框架扔掉
but to throw the process out completely or throw like the overlay of the process.
那种“嘿，我们现在处于流程的这个阶段”
The like, hey, we're at this point in the process like
那反而比以往任何时候都更重要
that is still more important than ever.
这很有意思，因为你在每个职能上都有背景
It's, it's really interesting because you have a background in every function.
别人看你的 LinkedIn，会看到工程师、设计师、产品经理、创始人
If people look at your LinkedIn, it's like engineer, designer, product manager, founder.
现在你负责桌面应用。我觉得设计不在你管辖范围内，对吗？
Now you oversee the desktop app. And I think design is not under your purview, is that right?
是有一个独立的设计团队，还是他们归你管？看是哪一周吧
Is there like a separate design team or are they under your. Depends on the week.
好。我们合作非常紧密。我们相信坐在一起
Okay. We work very closely together. Like we believe in walls sitting together,
深度嵌入，不管汇报线怎么算
being embedded like I reporting line.
我说不好，这每周都在变
I don't the shift, the shift weekly.
在 Codex 上的设计流程是什么样的？
What does the design process look like on on the Codex?
是的，关于角色坍缩、生存性角色坍缩已经写了很多
Yeah, there's been a lot written about role collapse, existential role collapse.
说再也没有角色边界了
There are no roles anymore.
我们没看到这种情况
We haven't seen that.
嗯，我们确实在 Codex 团队里看到比公司其他部分
Um, we've, we have seen more role collapse in the Codex org than I think other parts
以及整个经济体其他部分更多的角色坍缩
of the company and other parts of the economy.
我觉得部分原因是，这本来就是给工程师用的技术产品
I think part of this is that this was a technical product for engineers.
所以我们的设计师会说工程师的语言，对吧？
And so our designers speak engineer, right?
我们的产品经理会讲技术语言，也会写代码
Our product managers speak technical language and write code.
Alexander 有计算机科学硕士学位，这个……
Alexander has a master's degree in computer science, which is.
我可没有计算机科学硕士学位
I do not have a master's degree in computer science.
所以我们看到了很多角色坍缩，我觉得
Like, so we've seen a lot of role collapse and, and I think that, you know,
我们描述各团队如何协作的一种方式是
one of one of the ways that we describe how the groups work together is
现在角色之间的重叠比以前多得多
that there's significantly more overlap in the roles than there used to be.
每个人不再那么被那道界线定义
And everybody's sort of defined less by the fence and the boundaries of
不再被设计到哪、工程从哪开始来定义
where design stops and engineering starts,
而更多是被他们工作的平均位置定义，对吧？
but more the average of where they're working, right?
所以，如果你把
So like, you know, if you average up all of the things
设计团队某个人做的所有事平均一下，会有很多写代码的活儿
that somebody on our design team does, there's plenty of code writing things,
也有很多是产品工作，但平均下来
there's plenty of things that are product work, but on average,
他们的点大概落在这边，对吧？
like their dots over here, right?
如果你把它画到一张图上
If you draw, you draw it out on a diagram.
这其实也说明了流程的问题
And this sort of speaks to the process too,
尤其因为整个 Codex 应用都是靠内部试用的循环打磨出来的
especially because the entirety of the Codex app has been informed by the dogfooding loop.
我们所有人都想尽可能多地在应用里完成工作
There is a desire among all of us to try to do as much as possible in the app,
哪怕它还不是最好的工具，好让它能变成最好的工具
even when it's not the best tool, so that it can become the best tool.
所以很多设计我们都是通过用这个应用来做的，然后说，好
And so a lot of design we all work on by using the app and say, okay,
这里哪里不好用？
what's broken about this?
这是我们一直在做的一件事，就是
This is a whole thing we do, which is that we,
我们常常不去改善流程，而是为了能更好地做这件事去改进产品
we often don't improve our process so that we can make the product better to do it,
这是一种非常让人难受的状态
which is a deeply like, uncomfortable place to be in.
但每周都在变。我特别喜欢这个观点，就是你到底是什么？
But, you know, week to week, it's changing. I love this point so much that like, what are you?
你的角色就是你花时间做的事情的平均值
It's your role is the average of what you spend your time on.
如果你大部分工作是 PM 的活儿，那好，你现在就是 PM
If most of your work is PM, you work then, okay, you're a PM for now.
对。如果是工程，那你现在就是工程师
Yeah. If it's engineering, you're an engineer for now.
我觉得……OpenAI 是第一家把人称作 member of technical staff 的公司吗？
I feel like. Was OpenAI the first company to call people member of technical staff?
不是，我相信这可能是从 Xerox 开始的
No, I believe that this this might have started with Xerox.
是我实习的第一家公司
First company I interned at.
是一家叫 up there 的公司，也这么做，一直都有这说法，但
It was a company called up there, did the same thing, has been around, but it's,
现在这种叫法常见多了
it's, it's much more common now.
不过你知道，这在研究、以研究为核心的公司里算是一种传统，对吧？
But, you know, it is kind of a tradition in research, research focused companies, right?
好的，明白了。
Okay, got it.
所以它是从研究里长出来的，但我觉得这特别像，怎么说呢，
So it emerged from research, but I feel like it's such a, I don't know,
一种事情走向的信号，就是我们打算把所有人都叫做
sign of where things might be headed, this idea of we're just going to call everyone,
technical staff（技术团队成员），你的职能是不固定的。
member of technical staff, your function isn't set.
你不会被分进 PM 部门、工程部门或者设计部门这种格子里，
You're not like in this bucket of the PM org or the end org or the design org,
你觉得从长期看我们都会往那个方向走吗？
do you feel like that's where we all head long term?
你觉得职能划分还会继续存在吗？
Do you feel like functions will continue to exist?
比如还是有 PM 的技能组、工程的技能组
Like there's still the PM skill set and the engine skill set
还有设计的技能组。
and the design skill set.
对，人们会说，我是设计师。还是你觉得会变成，
Yeah. And people are, I'm a designer. Or do you think this is like,
大家都叫自己 builder（动手做产品的人）？
like people call a builder?
你觉得会不会出现一种坍缩，每个人都什么都做，
Do you feel like there's this collapse coming where everyone's everything and
而这就是未来？
that's just the future?
还是你觉得我们大体上还会继续被分工？
Or do you think we're going to continue to be mostly divided up?
是的，有一些事情是我担心的，我觉得，
Yeah, there are. There are some things that I'm afraid of, and I think that,
你知道，有些公司。
you know, some, some companies.
特别喜欢极端地追赶大家说会发生的
Like to be very extreme about getting onto the bandwagon of whatever people say is
那种趋势。
going to happen.
我觉得取消角色概念的一部分危险在于，
And I think part of the danger in eliminating the concept of roles is
它可能会危险地抹掉这样一个观念，
that it can dangerously eliminate the idea
就是这些事情是有专业性的、有可学的最佳实践的，对吧？
that things are specialties with knowables, best practices, right?
我听过很多公司说，我们要取消产品这个角色，
I've heard a lot of companies be like, we're getting rid of the product role,
顺便说一句，我觉得这是个糟糕的主意。
which I think is, by the way, a terrible idea.
嗯，每个人都会变成一个 builder，
Um, and everybody's just gonna be like a builder
结果就是，他们不重视产品这整套学科，
and then what happens is they don't like this whole discipline of product
而这套学科是积累出来的，有真正的最佳实践，
that's been built up and has like real best practices,
有真正试过、失败过的东西，有真正的流程。
real things that have been tried and failed and like real processes.
这些就被抛弃了，因为大家会说，哦，我写了点代码，对吧？
Like that just gets abandoned because people are like, oh, I wrote some code, right?
这不是个好状态。
Like, that's not a great place to be in.
我觉得那种界限，比如说，这不是你的地盘。
I think that the boundary of like so and so, like, this isn't your lane.
这部分消失，我是欢迎的。
I, I welcome that part going away.
但这里有个平衡，就是不是每个人都能什么都做，
But there's a balance here where it's like not everyone can work on everything for
一方面是广度，一方面是深度，对吧？
one, both in terms of breath and depth, right?
这就是为什么管理岗不会消失。嗯，
Like this is why managers are not going to go away. Um,
不是每个人都能什么都做。
not everybody can work on everything.
而且每个学科都有它的技能成分，
And also like every discipline has a skill component to it,
我觉得很多工程师都有个毛病，就是不承认这一点，比如觉得，
which I think a lot of engineers are guilty of not recognizing that, like, well,
工程是有技能门槛的。
engineering is a skill to it.
它是写代码。而其他角色只是些人在瞎晃悠。
It's writing code. And, like, other roles are just people vibrating.
但其实不是，事情不是这样的，对吧？
It's like, no, that's not how it works, right?
嗯，就像，是的，你会用 Excel，但你不一定能进财务团队干活，
Um, like, yes, you can use Excel you but you cannot work on the finance team,
对，就是这类事情，对吧？
right that is like that kind of stuff, right?
对，我觉得还有一点就是，你想不想做这份工作？
Yeah, I think there's also just like, do you want to be doing this work?
对。我想不想？
Yeah. Do I want to be?
我觉得更多的是，现在其实是，换角色更容易了，
I think more of it's that actually now is like, it's easier to switch roles,
学最佳实践更容易了，
it's easier to learn the best practices,
更容易做到不把你在一个角色里的效率，绑死在会不会用
it's easier to not tie your effectiveness in a role with the ability to use the
那个具体工具上，对吧？
exact tool, right?
更多的是，你能不能进入这种思维方式，
It's more of like, can you get yourself into this mindset,
搞清楚哪些有效、哪些无效，然后专注去做，对吧？
learn which things work and which don't and then like, focus on it, right?
我曾经很长一段时间觉得自己不该当软件工程师，
Like, I spent so long feeling like I should not be a software engineer
因为我不在乎汇编语言，也不在乎背 TypeScript 语法，
because I didn't care about, like, assembly language or memorizing typescript syntax,
你知道，这些角色里一直都有一些部分，
you know, and it's like there have always been parts of these roles that are
是那种设门槛的，会说，不行。
that sort of gatekeeping that are like, well, no.
就好像擅长这个角色，就等于擅长这个工具。
This like being good at this role is being good at this tool.
我觉得这正是开始被瓦解的东西。
And I think that's what's kind of starting to erode.
我不这么看。我觉得大家把这些都夸大了。
I just don't. I think people take this, they hyperbolize all of this.
你们 Codex 团队现在是什么样子？有多少工程师、设计师、PM？
What does your team look like on, on, on the Codex team. How many engineers, designers, PMS?
现在团队的构成大概是怎样的？
What's kind of like the makeup of the team right now?
每次有人问我，Codex 团队有多少人？
Every time people ask me, like, how many people are on the Codex team?
你还记得我怎么回答的吗？
Do you remember my answer to this?
我会说，大概在 10 人到几千人之间。
I'm like, it's somewhere between 10 and a few thousand.
这听着像敷衍，但其实
I mean, it's like a fake answer, but it's,
也很真实，因为我们把它看成这里所有人工作的总和。
it's real in that we do see this as the combination of what everybody works on here.
比如投入到模型研究里的一切，还有
Like everything that goes into model research, everything that goes into how,
让模型擅长 computer use 和浏览器操作的一切，
you know, models are good at Cua and browser use, everything about how, you know,
关于模型个性的一切，围绕它的所有产品工作，比如
model personality, all of the product work around, you know,
前端基础设施，还有所有用户相关的部分。
front end infrastructure, all of the user.
这一切同时构成了这个产品，
Like all of it is this product at the same time,
但我们并不是每天都在接收成千上万人
we are not accepting PRs daily from thousands
随心所欲提交的 PR。
and thousands of people on whatever they want.
所以我们有一个团队，工程师是两位数，
Um, so we got a team, uh, double digits of engineers,
设计这边大概是它的一半。
probably half that on the design side.
还有几位产品人，不过
Um, you know, a few product people, although, you know,
这里的产品更像是一种区域防守式协作。
product here is kind of more of a zone defense play.
我觉得在 Codex 这边，或者说桌面应用这边，
And I think one thing that is very common around among everybody on the Codex side
大家有一个非常普遍的共同点，
or on the desktop side is.
就是主动性和品位，对吧？
Agency and taste, right?
很多人是前创始人，或者在大公司里做过类似创始人的事。
A lot of former founders or people who were at larger companies doing founder shaped things.
很多品位极高的人。在 OpenAI，我们让团队可以做得很大，
Um, a lot of people with with immense taste at OpenAI we let teams get very large
我们没说不要管理，但团队确实相当大，对吧？
so we haven't said hey there's no management but like the teams are quite large, right?
大部分是 IC。
It's mostly ICS.
我觉得用“区域防守”这个词来形容产品工作挺贴切的。
Um, and I think that's good use this term, zone defense for product work.
是的，这确实很有意思。
And yeah, that's really interesting.
它也和设计上的转变有点对应，就像
It kind of maps to the design kind of shift also, just like, yeah,
你的角色更多是管理和协调。
you're there to kind of manage and coordinate.
能多讲讲这具体是什么样子吗？
Talk a little bit more about what that looks like.
对产品人来说，区域防守是什么样的？
What does zone defense look like for a product person?
我和 Alexander 就这个比喻聊过很多次，
Yeah, and I have had a lot of conversations with, with Alexander about this,
大意是，如果两个产品人配合得太紧密，
this analogy, which is that like if two product people are working too closely,
这往往不是个好信号，作为一个产品组织，
that's often not a good signal and that like you kind of want like as a product org.
你其实想做一种力导向式的分布，去想
You sort of want to do this like force directed activity where you're like,
空缺在哪里，尤其在这个新世界里，筛选、引导
where are the gaps, especially in this new world where curation and like steering
和对齐占了很大一部分工作，你会想
and alignment is a lot of things where you're like.
到处都是混乱，大家把各种想法四处抛出来。
There's a ton of chaos happening on, people throwing ideas all over the place.
对，那种自上而下、做一年规划的方式行不通了。
Right. The whole like top down, you know, year long planning thing, not gonna work.
所以现在我们需要有品位的人，从最初一路引导，
And so now it's like we need the taste makers to guide things from inception to what
直到产品该有的样子。
the product should be.
这意味着你基本上想覆盖整个公司。
And that means you basically want company coverage.
于是你分散开来，问：好，谁最擅长什么？
And so you spread out and you say, all right, who's like, who's best at what?
我们彼此之间拉开一些空间，这样就能全面覆盖，对吧。
Let's create some space between us so that we got full coverage, right.
大概就是这么运作的。
And that's kind of how it goes.
然后你去填补空缺，你会说，
And then you fill in the gaps and you're like, look,
我们想招有产品思维的工程师。
like we want to hire engineers who are product-minded.
我们不希望
Like we don't.
变成那种情况，就是
We don't want it to be that, you know,
一群人写了一堆代码，还需要
we've got a bunch of people writing a bunch of code that needs, like,
整个团队去审查它的产品一致性，对吧？
full team reviewing it for, like, product coherence, right?
我们希望每个人都具备这些能力，但我觉得
Like, we want everyone to have these skills, but I think, like,
大家深耕的方向必须改变，对吧？
what people go deep on has to change, right?
这绝对是我一直在注意到的一条线索，
This is definitely a thread I've been noticing over
在和你这样的人聊天时反复出现——现在最有价值的人。
and over with talking to folks like you is the, the most valuable person right now.
最有价值的那类人之一。
One of the most valuable.
能把一个想法从构思做到完成，还有品位判断出这东西很棒的人。
Someone that could take an idea from idea to done with the taste to know this is great.
是的，就是全程带着一种把它做到极致的执着去推进，
Yeah, just like shepherding throughout this obsession with making it awesome,
就是这种高主动性、高品位的人。
like this kind of high agency, high taste person.
没错，正如你所说。
Exactly. As you describe.
你是不是就是这样想的——我们要招什么样的人，
Is that, is that kind of the way you think about here's who we're hiring,
谁能在这个新世界里做得很好。
here's who's gonna do really well in this new world.
对，我觉得这就是现在最核心的部分。
Yeah, I think that that's, that's the core piece right now.
这也反映了我对 IC 和管理岗的看法，
And it, it also speaks to how I sort of see IC versus management,
那就是并不是管理岗要消失了。
which is that it's not that management is going away.
也不是说人人都是 IC，而是现在每个人都有点两者兼具，对吧？
It's not that everyone's an IC, but like everyone's kind of both now, right?
如果你是 IC，你不会再一个字符一个字符地敲代码了，对吧？
If you're an IC, you're not typing code out character by character, right?
你是在管理某些东西，你在管理 agents。
Like, you are managing something. You're managing agents.
你在管理，就是那些正在进行的工作，
You're managing, you know, like you're managing work that is happening, right,
这些工作汇聚起来去完成某件事。
that comes together to do a certain thing.
如果你是带团队的管理者，你做的其实是同一件事，只是在不同的，
If you're a manager of teams, you're doing the same thing just at a different, like,
不同的颗粒度上，对吧？
different granularity, right?
我通常看重的，显然是对这个领域的掌控力，
I generally look for, like, obviously, command over the discipline,
但还有那种品位，能说出，
but then the taste to say like.
你会有用不完的 token，
You're gonna have unlimited tokens
我们不能只是随便糊弄，你得能判断出，
and I don't like we can't just be doing slap like you need to be able to determine
在这个内容无限多的世界里，什么是信号，什么是噪声。
what signal, what's noise like in a world of just infinite content.
说说规划吧。
Mention planning.
以现在这个变化速度，做 roadmap 规划变得非常难。
Uh, at the pace things are moving, it's become very hard to plan roadmaps.
对，我能想象，尤其是在你们这个领域，
Yeah. I imagine, especially in your world, uh,
大家一直都因为这件事对我很不满。
people are very frustrated with me all the time on this.
对，因为东西一直在发布，一直在变，对吧。
Yes. Because things are just constantly shipping. Things are changing. Right.
你在团队里是怎么做规划的？
How do you plan on, on, on your team?
你大概会往前看多远？一份规划长什么样？
What's kind of like how far ahead are you thinking? And what does a plan look like?
是一个表格吗？是 MD 文件吗？规划的产出到底是什么形式？
Is it like a spreadsheet? Is it MD file? What? What's kind of the output of a plan?
说实话，我不觉得我们在这方面有什么革命性的做法。
Yeah, I don't, I don't think we do anything revolutionary on that.
我们在规划上并不高明。
We're not clever about planning.
我觉得基本思路是，一件事越是短期，
I think like the basic gist is the shorter term something is,
就越需要细节。
the more detail it needs.
并不是说我们不做九个月后的规划，而是，
And then it's not that we don't plan for nine months out, it's that,
那部分必须保持很模糊，因为你现在给一个九个月的规划，
that just has to stay very hazy because any amount of precision
加入任何精确度，都是虚假的精确，
that you add to a nine month plan right now is false precision
你只是在浪费时间。
and like you're just going to waste time.
你可以说点方向，对吧？但我们规划的东西，
But you can say stuff, right? But like nothing that we planned.
我觉得研究那边不一样。
I think research is different.
我这里不代表研究团队，
So I'm not speaking for research here,
但在应用这边，做产品的时候，
but like on the applied side when we do products,
你在十一月做的任何规划，可能对十二月还成立，
like anything that you could have planned in November may have been true for
但和实际发生的情况不一样，对吧？
December, but like isn't what happened, right?
所以很难，做规划真的非常难。
So it's hard. Like it is really hard to do planning.
我们通常需要知道，模型在什么时间点大概能做到什么。
We generally need to know like what do we think models are able to do on what timeline.
在我上一家公司，我目睹了一个转变，
And my last company, I kind of saw this shift
我们开始用模型来驱动功能，
where we were starting to use the models to drive features
然后原来的产品流程就崩了。
and the product process fell down.
基本上就变成，我们把所有想做的东西列出来，
It basically had to be like, let's list out all of the things
那些接下来一两年我们感兴趣做的东西。
that we think we are interested in doing for the next year or two.
我们把它们全都做成原型，判断哪些现在成熟了，
Let's prototype all of them, decide which things are ready now,
剩下的就先放着，慢慢发酵。
and then just let the others sit and bake.
然后每次模型有新的飞跃，
And then every time there's like a new leap in models,
就换上新模型再试一遍，因为，
let's try that thing again with it swapped out because, like,
一个功能好不好，前提完全取决于模型，
the whole premise of whether features were good or not were based on whether they
是否足够聪明，而不是功能本身的形态。所以这是个很好的例子，说明，
were smart enough, not the shape of them. So this is a great story about.
就说 Codex 应用吧。
The Codex app I like.
我非常确信，我们二月发布的 Codex 应用，
I am very confident that the Codex app that we released in February,
如果它当时就已经做好，
if that had been ready.
放在十一月，它在市场上一定会失败。
In November, it would have absolutely failed in the market.
而唯一的区别就是十一月到二月之间的模型，对吧。
And the. The only difference was the models between November and February, right.
我觉得这里面很有讲究，
And I, I think like there's a lot to that,
同样形态的这个产品，我觉得它的，
that this product with the exact same shape I think would have like its,
它的结果会因为仅仅几个月的时间差而完全不同。
its outcomes were totally different depending on just a few months of timing.
本期节目由 Mercury 赞助。彻底不一样的银行服务，
This episode is brought to you by Mercury. Radically different banking,
深受超过 30 万创业者的喜爱，现在还带来了 command 功能。
loved by over 300,000 entrepreneurs and now with command.
我已经是 Mercury 的客户超过六年了。
I've been a customer of Mercury's for over 6 years.
我从没想过要离开。
I have never once thought about leaving.
Mercury 基本上就是让做产品的人、而不是银行家来做银行的结果。
Mercury is basically what happens when banking is built by product people, not by bankers.
他们让开发票、转账变得非常简单，甚至可以说很有趣，
They make it so easy, dare I say fun, to send invoices, move money around,
给团队成员设置虚拟卡也一样。
set up virtual cards for folks on my team.
你的银行有 API、终端、原生 CLI 或者支持 AI 的 MCP server 吗？
Does your bank have an API, a terminal, native CLI or an AI ready MCP server?
我看没有。
I don't think so.
最近他们还推出了 command，
And just recently they launched command,
这是一个直接内置在 Mercury 里的对话式界面，
a conversational interface built directly into Mercury,
它就像你的财务操作员。
which acts as your financial operator.
我一直用 command 转账，弄清楚我在哪些类别上
I've been using command to transfer money around to figure out what categories I've
花钱最多，还能分析我的现金流。
been spending the most money in, analyze my cash flows.
就在今天，我还用它查了过去一年从某个赞助商那里赚了多少。
And just today I used it to find out how much I've made from a specific sponsor over the past year.
我只是问：过去一年我从 X 那里赚了多少？
I just asked how much have I made from X over the past year?
十秒后就有了答案。真是太酷了。
10 seconds later I have an answer. It is so freaking cool.
访问 mercury.com 了解更多，几分钟就能在线申请。
Visit mercury.com to learn more and apply online in minutes.
Mercury 是一家金融科技公司，不是受 FDIC 保险的银行。
Mercury is a fintech company, not an FDIC insured bank.
银行服务由 Choice Financial Group 和 Column N.A. 提供，均为 FDIC 成员。
Banking services provided through Choice Financial Group and column na members FDIC.
这绝对是这期播客里的一条主线，
This is definitely a threat on this podcast,
就是去做那些现在还不行、但等模型变强后就能成的东西。
is build things that are not yet working that will work when the model gets better.
还有另一条主线，是关于野心的。
And there's this kind of other threat of ambition.
对你要做的事情更有野心一些。
Be more ambitious with the things you take on.
所以这算是你做事的一种方式吗，就是
So is this just like a way you approach things is just like,
先做一堆现在可能还不行的东西。
let's just build a bunch of things that may not work yet.
先把它们放着，等模型跟上来。
We'll just have them around and wait for a model to catch up.
是这种做法吗？对，我觉得我们有很多这样的情况。
Is that kind of the approach? Yeah, I think we have a lot of that.
我觉得难点有时在于，你得再次非常清楚地知道
I think sometimes the challenges like you have to be very clear again about what
这处在设计流程的哪个阶段。
stage of the design process that's in.
人们还有这种肌肉记忆，觉得：噢，我给这东西写了代码，
People still have this muscle memory of like, oh, I wrote the code for this thing,
所以我们就应该把它发布出去。
therefore we should put it out there.
但其实不是，不不不。
It's like, no, no, no.
那只意味着你现在有了一个产物，可以用来对未来的模型做测试，对吧？
That means you have an artifact now that we can test against for into future models, right?
嗯，我们应用里内置的浏览器就是这样，
Um, this happens with the in app browser in the app that we have,
我们其实有一个能跑的版本。
right like we had a kind of a working version.
回到 Atlas，我们在 Atlas 里就让 agent 跑起来了，你知道，
I mean, go back to Atlas, we had agent working inside of Atlas and, you know,
那挺酷的。
that was pretty cool.
在那之前 ChatGPT 里有 operator，对吧？那没成功。想法很酷。
We had operator before that in ChatGPT, right? That didn't work out. Very cool idea.
你可以在 Operator、Atlas、Codex、
Like there's some thread that you can draw between Operator Atlas Code, Codex,
ChatGPT 之间画出一条线，本质上是同一个功能，
ChatGPT, that's like fundamentally the same feature
但用不同的智能水平重新发布它，会彻底改变结果，
but the re releasing of it with different intelligence totally changes the outcome
所以我会劝大家别固执地觉得：不行，这个不管用，
here and so I push people not to be stubborn about like, no, this isn't working,
所以是个烂功能。不是这样的。
so it's a bad feature. It's like, no.
它可能只是还没到时候。嗯，还有一点，尤其是在研究里。
It might not be ready yet. Um, there's also this aspect of, especially in research.
总有一种想做到最有野心的冲动，会说：好吧，但在极限情况下，
There's always a desire to be the most ambitious and to say, okay, but at the limit,
模型就能做到这个，可这在产品那一侧就是行不通。
the model can just do this and it just doesn't work on the product side.
比如你回看最初的 Codex 发布，
Like if you if you go back to the original Codex release,
基本上它就是所谓的 Codex Web，
basically what it was is it said it was Codex Web
而它并不适合用来交互。
and it wasn't good for interacting with.
就是你给模型一个任务，它就会跑开去执行，
It was like you give the model a task and it's going to go off, do the task,
完成后再回来交给你。
come back to you with it finished.
听起来没那么激进。问题在于，
Like doesn't sound that radical. The problem is like,
它把任务做得不够好。
it didn't do the task that well.
它确实写了代码，写得也不错，
Like, it wrote code. It was, it was it was good,
但那种形态出得太早了。
but it was like that form factor was too early.
然后 Claude Code 出来了，完全本地，没连到云端，嗯，
And then the cloud code comes out totally local, like not hooked up to the cloud, um,
它不假装那么，它没那么 AGI 上头，对吧？
doesn't pretend to be as, it's not as AGI Pelt, right?
它会问你问题，会待在那儿，
It's like, gonna ask you questions, gonna sit there,
你没法把整个事全甩给它。
you can't just delegate your life to it.
那反而好用多了，对吧？因为那才是当时模型该有的定位，对吧？
That worked way better, right? Cause that's the point that the models were out there, right?
所以我们当时算是太 AGI 上头了。
So we were like, we were too AGI piled for the moment.
我觉得，我经常想到这方面的这个教训。
And I think like I, I think about that lesson a lot on this stuff.
以前是这样的，产品在市场上失败，会告诉你很多信息，
It used to be that, you know, failing in market told you all these things about the
关于产品的形态，关于产品的传达方式。
shape of the product, about the communication of the product.
而现在是，不，你可能得把这东西发布六次，
And now it's like, no, you might need to release this thing six different times
它才能真正跑通。
before it works.
而这期间，产品的形态可能根本没变。
And that might, like, the shape might not change at all.
听你讲做产品要考虑的这么多变量，真的很有意思，
There's like, it's so interesting to hear about all the variables you have to think
关于做产品时要考虑的。
about building product.
现在有模型和研究的时间线，还有它会变多聪明。
Now there's the timeline for the models and the research and how smart it gets.
还有人们能不能理解，原来可以这样在云端
There's like people's ability to even understand this is how you could build
构建软件，而且这就是未来。
software in the cloud and this is the future.
就是让大家为这个新未来做好准备，然后，呃，
Like get people prepared for this new future and then just, uh,
你作为一个团队能构建出什么。
what you can build as a team.
我很喜欢那个 Codex 的例子，因为它又回到了雄心这个话题。
And I love that Codex example. Cuz comes back to this idea of ambition.
我想听听，你有没有这样的思路：就是要
And I want to hear if there's anything there for you of just this thread of just be
更有雄心，因为这些模型能做到的远超你的想象。
more ambitious because these models can do so much more than even imagine.
有时候对市场来说太超前了，大家还没准备好。
And sometimes it's too ambitious for the market and they're not ready for it.
但你会去想这个问题吗，
But you think about that at all,
就是推动团队更有雄心，因为现在做那些
just like pushing your team to be more ambitious because it's
过去感觉难到离谱的事，现在容易太多了。
so much easier to just do things that may be felt crazy hard in the past.
是的，这是个核心挑战。
Yeah, this is a core challenge.
一旦有了一个已经存在的产品或功能，
Once, once there's a product that exists or a feature that exists,
大家很容易去挑小毛病、做微优化。
it's really easy for people to find paper cuts and micro optimize.
这也是应该的。Twitter 上的人很喜欢提醒我们这点，
And they should. And people on Twitter like to remind us of this
我很感谢他们。
and I thank them for that.
大家确实应该关注已有的功能，
Like people should be focused on the features that exist
让它们更可靠、更好。
and making them more reliable and better.
但这也是为什么我们这里有一种自下而上探索的文化。
But this, you know, this is why we also have a culture of bottoms up exploration here.
因为有时候，就像 Codex 应用出现，
Because sometimes in the same way the Codex app came
在某种程度上颠覆了 ChatGPT 一样，
and disrupted ChatGPT in some way, right,
这个东西也会被未来的某个项目颠覆。
this thing will get disrupted by a future effort.
这也是设计的一部分，就是一个团队没法总是
And that's that's part of the design is that like you can't always as one team,
既擅长颠覆的部分，又擅长
be good at both the disruptive piece and the, like,
维护产品和保证质量的部分。
maintaining a product and its quality piece.
到某个点，你得设计一个能兼顾两者的流程。
At some point, you gotta design a process that allows for both.
稍微拉远一点看。
Kind of zooming out a little bit.
如果你想想我们一路走来的过程，
If you think about the progression
AI 影响我们做产品的这个进程，
that we've been on of AI impacting how we build product,
我们走了多远简直不可思议，就像你说的，
it's like insane how far we've come from, as you said,
我们以前所有代码都是手写的。
we used to write all our code by hand.
从充满匠心的人类手写代码，到 AI 写我们 100% 的代码。
Like artistically created human code to AI, writing 100 of our code to you.
其实可以这么说，现在写代码就是在引导 AI。
Actually put it this way that now like, coding is steering the AI.
当你想我的代码有多大比例是 AI 写的，
And like, when you think about what percentage of my code is written by AI,
差不多就是我要把它引导到正确方向多少次，
it's almost like how many times that I have to steer it in the right direction is
这就是 AI 版的写代码，而现在还有 agents、循环
the AI version of coding and now that there's like agents and loops
这些东西。
and all these things.
从你看到的来说，大家做产品的最新前沿是什么？
What's kind of the latest frontier from what you've seen of how people are building?
是循环吗？
Is it loops?
还是有别的？就是那些最 AGI 上头、最 AI 领先的团队，
Is there something else of just like the most AI pilled, AI forward teams,
他们现在是怎么运作的，可能大家还不知道。
here's how they operate now that people may not be aware of.
是啊，循环已经是上周的事了，老兄。
Yeah, I mean, loops are so last week, man.
我们聊过这个，呃，一个大问题总是，
I mean, we talked about this, um, you know, one of the big questions is always, well,
产品里有多少是 AI 写的？
how much of the product is AI written?
这个问题总是很难回答，因为
And it's always hard to answer that question cause
如果你用去年的标准来衡量，那就是，
if you're using the goalposts from last year, it's like, well,
我们现在产品 100% 都是 AI 写的代码。
100% of our product right now is AI written code.
所以问题更像是，好吧，那，
So the question is more like, well, okay, fine, is,
这些代码是有监督写的，还是无监督写的？
is the code written supervised versus unsupervised, right?
这就完全是另一回事了。
And that's like a totally different thing.
我欢迎标准不断被抬高，因为这意味着我们在产品上有进展。
I welcome the moving of goalposts because that means we're making product progress.
这方面已经有很多探索，比如自主的，
There have been a lot of explorations here around like autonomous,
自主开发的软件，嗯，还有很多 harness 工程之类的东西，
autonomously developed software, um, a lot of like harness engineering stuff,
各种不同的探索，比如说，好吧，
a lot of different explorations on like, okay, well,
要是隔夜进来对代码库做一次垃圾回收，把它清理干净会怎样，
what if you came in overnight and did garbage collection of the code base to clean
对吧？有一件事我觉得。
it up, right? One thing that I think.
所有模型现在都有这个问题，就是它们通常会增加复杂度。
All models suffer with right now is just they, they usually increase complexity.
如果哪家公司的研究团队在听，
If research is listening at any company,
请让模型更擅长删代码。
please make the models better at deleting code.
嗯，但你知道，这一点现在会成为一个问题，
Um, but you know, that becomes a problem right now
当你想让开发完全进入自动驾驶模式时，
when you try to put development completely on autopilot
而且人这边和代码库这边都有问题。
and it's both on the the human side and the code base side.
比如功能需求，对吧？
So like feature requests, right?
你要怎么教模型该做哪些功能、忽略哪些，
You know, how do you teach a model which features to build, which ones to ignore,
哪些该归到一起、稍微重新组织一下。
which ones to kind of like group together and reframe a little bit.
你要怎么教模型构建正确的抽象，对吧？
How do you teach the model how to build the right abstractions, right?
这些都在变得越来越好。
Like all of this is getting better.
嗯，我觉得我们还没到那个地步，
Um, I don't think we're at a place yet where we're like,
就是直接设一个循环，让它去改进这个应用，
we're just gonna set up a loop that's, like, improve the app, you know,
让它去听 Twitter、听 Slack、听邮件，
and listens to Twitter and listens to Slack and listens to email and like,
我们还没到那一步。
we're not there yet.
但我们在努力，我们在努力让它实现。你觉得我们会走到那一步吗？
But we are. We are. We're trying to make it happen. Do you think we'll get there?
你觉得我们会不会走到那种地步，就是「增长」，「赢/目标」，
Do you think we'll get to a place where it's just like grow, like win slash goal,
「赚钱」，比如「给我赚十亿美元」，「赢」，「赢下市场」。
make money, like make me a billion dollars, win, win the market.
我不知道，老兄。我不太会去说「永远不会」或者「永远会」这种话。
I don't know, man. Like I, I am not in the business of saying never or always or whatever.
是啊。作为产品负责人、工程负责人，你在工作中是怎么用 AI 的？
Yeah. How are you using AI in your work as product leader, engineer leader?
是啊，你有哪些用法，
Yeah. What are some ways that you use it
可能大家还没意识到这个应用能这么用。
that maybe people may not be aware they can use the app for.
是啊，我觉得我现在拥有全世界最好的工作。
Yeah, I think I have the best job in in the world right now.
嗯，但让它非常有意思的一点是，
Um, but one of the things that makes it very fun is that
当我们开发最初的 Codex 应用时，
when we were developing the original Codex app,
我个人的目标是把它做成我写代码用的工具，对吧？
the goal for me personally was to make it the thing that I wrote the code with, right?
我当时想，我得让它在开发上做得足够好，
I was like, I need to make this so good at development
好到我能用它来构建 Codex 应用，而当时的 Codex 应用
that I can build the Codex app with this and the Codex app at
那时候是一个开发工具，对吧？
that time was a development tool, right?
我们把这个做得超级快。就是内部试用循环。
And we did that like super quick. Dog fooding loop.
因为你有自己的个人试用循环，你会想，噢，
Cuz you got your personal dog fooding loop where you're like, oh,
比如我做不了这件事。
like I can't do this thing.
我该把它修好，这样我就能做这件事，现在我能做了，现在我能做
I should fix that so that I can do the thing now I can do the thing now I can do
更多事情了，对吧？
more things, right?
嗯，我们把它发布了，然后下一个挑战是，嘿，
Um, you know, we released that and then the next challenge was, hey,
大家开始用它做一些形态不一样的事情了，对吧？
people are starting to do some different shaped things with us, right?
现在我需要把它做大，所以我得招几个人来帮忙。
And now I, you know, need to grow this and so I need to hire a few people and help.
于是我的角色也变了，就在同一时间，
So then, like, my role changed at the same time
这个应用的角色也需要改变。
that the role of the app needed to change.
所以我想，好，我得在这里做更多的产品探索。
So I'm like, okay, I need to do more product discovery here.
我得找到合适的循环，去了解每个人在做什么，
I need to figure out the right loops for seeing what everybody's working on
并把偏离轨道的事情拉回来。
and steering things that are off track.
于是突然之间，我就开始用 Codex 应用来做这些事了，对吧？
And so all of a sudden, that's what I started using the Codex app for, right?
我确实还是会写代码。
I did still write code.
就是我一直在努力让自己对它的用法，对齐我们
It's like I've tried to align my own usage of it with the problem
正在试图解决的问题，对吧？
that we're trying to solve, right?
现在我会想，我需要做一个电子表格把这个建模出来。
And now I'm like, I need to build a spreadsheet that models this out.
我需要做一次，你知道的，
I need to kind of do a, you know,
对所有投入的努力做一次内部深度调研，
internal deep research on all of the efforts
这些努力都投在了这个研究领域，为的是下一个版本，
that have gone into this area of research for the next version of this,
五月有一次发布，或者一系列发布。
there's a release or a series of releases in may.
差不多五月吧，那次发布给 Codex 应用引入了应用内浏览器的 computer use
Ish, that introduced the in app browser computer use
和 artifact 创建功能，我觉得那次
and artifact creation to the Codex app that was, I think,
是我们「让几乎所有人都能用上 Codex」的发布，大家都知道 vibe coding 这个词。
our codexes for almost everyone release and everybody knows the term vibe coding.
我觉得那算是我们第一次 vibe 协调式的发布，当时我有一个，
I think that was like our first vibe coordinated release where like I had a,
就是在某个 Notion 文档里，记着所有要做的事
you know, Notion doc somewhere with everything that needed to happen
我当时在做自动化，比如自动去收集各种更新
and I was like automating, like going out to gather updates.
从 pull request、从 Slack 频道里收集，然后更新状态追踪表
from pull requests from Slack channels and like updating the status tracker
现在这已经很常见了，但在当时
and like now this is pretty commonplace, but at the time,
我感觉自己站在管理产品发布的最前沿
I felt like I was at the bleeding edge of like how to manage a product release.
简单说，我用 Codex 应用的方式，基本上就是
In short, like the way that I use the Codex app is basically like what,
我的工作演变成了什么样，以及怎么让它能帮我做完所有我要做的事
what has my job grown into and how do I make this thing able to do everything I need to do?
嗯，我早上起床
Um, I will get up in the morning,
我会看到一份每日简报，汇总了我加入的 3000 个 Slack
I will see the daily brief that I have from like everything from the 3,000 Slack
频道里的所有信息，比如哪些事需要我关注
channels that I'm in, like which things need my attention,
我可以回一句消息，说，好的
I can kind of message back and be like, all right.
给我五个问题，我来回答，我可以这么做
Give me five questions and I'll answer them and I can, you know, do that.
你是怎么设置的？别人要设置这个，工作流是怎样的？
How do you set that up? What's like the workflow to for somebody to set that up?
对，这听起来太棒了。再说一次
Yeah, that sounds amazing. Again,
我觉得这里面很多东西我们还在探索阶段
I I think we're still in the like discovery phase on on a lot of this.
所以现在，就像是我在做一个，不是 Notion
And, and so right now, it's like I'm making not a notion
而是一个定时任务，写着，去过一遍我的 Slack 频道
that says or scheduled task that says like, go through my Slack channels.
这些是我关心的、我认为最重要的事
These are the things that I care about and think are most important.
所以我还在定义
And, you know, so I'm still kind of defining
比如这些是要留意的事，分成不同类别
that like these are things to watch out for, different categories.
比如，这里有些背景信息，然后我会
Like, here's some context and, you know, I'll, I'll, you know,
把它设置成一个自动化任务
that'll get set up as a automated task.
前几次运行时，可能需要一些引导
And then first few times it runs, it might need some steering.
幸运的是，用这个应用
And luckily with this app, you know,
我不用去研究怎么编辑指令
I don't have to find out how to edit the instructions.
我可以直接说，嘿，下次运行时
I can just be like, hey, next time this runs, like,
能不能改成关注这个，或者把这条工作线的优先级降低？
can you please worry about this instead, or can you deemphasize this work stream?
或者，嘿，发生了这件事，但简报里没提到
Or, hey, this thing happened and it didn't come up in a brief like,
你能确保把这类内容纳入吗，这样我可以一路调教它
can you make sure that stuff in the shape so I can kind of coach it along the way?
它会更新它的方式
It'll update the way that it.
通知我的方式，诸如此类。太棒了
Notifies me, stuff like that. Amazing.
我觉得未来，这一直是一个核心问题
I think in the future that like this is this has been a core problem with the
就是聊天机器人这种形态，对吧？
chatbot shape, right?
就是我知道怎么设置这个
Is that I know how to set this up.
我有时间去设置，因为对我来说，设置它本身就是产品探索
I have time to set this up because for me it's product discovery to set it up.
但如果你不在 OpenAI 工作，不在开发这个
But if you're not working at OpenAI, not developing this,
你并不想去搞懂这一堆东西
like you don't want to have to figure out all this stuff.
所以我们需要把这种形态想清楚
Like we, we, we need to like figure out that, that shape of things.
对
Yeah.
我听下来的意思是，我觉得人们没意识到
What I'm hearing here is I don't think people realize that, uh,
你的应用可以很像 OpenClaw 那样工作
your app can act a lot like OpenClaw.
对，确实是
Yeah, you was. It was.
大家当时都很兴奋，就是你直接跟它说，设置这个
People were so excited about like, you just talk to it, set up this thing,
每天帮我盯着这件事，然后告诉我情况怎么样
check on this thing for me every day and then tell me what's going on.
对，它开始成为所有这些产品的一部分
Like, yeah, like it's starting to become a part of all these, all the products.
这很棒
Which is amazing.
所以别人要设置的话，就是在应用里直接说
So the way somebody would set this up is they just talk within the app and say,
我想设置一个自动化来做这件事
I want to set up an automation to do this.
看看我的 Slack，这些是我想做的事。对，很好
Look at my Slack and these are the things I want to do. Yeah, great.
对
Yeah.
然后应用会说，好的
And the app will say, you know, yeah,
它会帮你设置，如果它还没有 Slack 连接器，它会说
it'll set it up for you if it doesn't have a Slack connector, it'll say,
我可以添加 Slack 连接器吗？
can I add the Slack connector?
要还是不要？你点“要”就行
Yes or no? You can hit yes to that.
对，我们至少能做到的是，如果你不知道怎么在应用里做
Yeah, like the least that we can do is make it so that if you don't know how to do
某件事，直接问它就行
something in the app, they could just ask it.
对，没错。我觉得这还不够
Yeah, right. Yeah. I don't think that's enough,
但我觉得这是我们至少能做到的
but I think that's the least we can do.
对，一个好例子是，我做了一个小应用
Yeah, a good example is I built this little app
用来过滤收件箱里的垃圾邮件
that filter spammy email from my inbox.
每封进来的邮件，我用 Codex 做了这个，每封进来的邮件，
So every email that comes in, and I built this in Codex, every email that comes in,
它会看一眼，然后判断，这是不是那种我不想看的推销冷邮件，
it looks at it and decides, is this unsolicited kind of cold emaily stuff
然后给它打标签，放到别的地方去。
that I don't want to look at and labels it and puts it somewhere else.
为了设置这个，其中一步是你得进到 Google Cloud
And to set that up, one of the steps was you have to go into like the Google Cloud
Console，把那些 pub sub 之类的 API 和触发器都配好。
Console and set up all these pub sub hub, bub API things and triggers.
不知道你用没用过那个界面，特别烦，又特别慢。
I don't know if you ever use that interface. It's like so annoying and slow.
我就想，等等，要是让你来做会怎样？
So I was like, wait, what if I ask you to do it?
我就说，好，那你帮我搞定。它就直接，这就是你说的 computer use。
And I was like, okay, cool, do this for me. And it just, you describe computer use.
我以前从没在自己电脑上见过这种事。是啊，
I've never actually seen this happen on my computer before. Yeah,
它就直接接管我的电脑，开始操作。
it just takes over my computer and starts going there.
它就像，我不管你有没有 connector，哥们。
It's like, I don't care if you don't have a connector, man.
我直接开始点就是了。对，然后它就自己搞明白了。
I'll just start clicking. Yeah, and it figures it out.
看着它自己干活，真的很疯狂，
It's crazy just to like watch it doing its thing,
它在设计各种边界的决策逻辑，
designing the decision boundary between connectors,
什么时候用应用内浏览器，什么时候用你连接好的
when to use the in app browser versus your Chrome extension
Chrome 扩展，什么时候用 computer use。
that's connected versus computer use.
对，很有意思，而且全都是靠它自己摸索出来的。
Yeah, was interesting and all done through just like feeling it out.
我前几天看到一个很棒的 Twitter thread，里面描述了这三种，
I saw a great Twitter thread the other day where they describe all these three
以及各自的用途。
and what you use it for.
对，这个人描述得非常好。
Yeah. So this person described it really well.
这些个人工作流很有意思，因为有些真的特别契合。
These personal workflows are really interesting because some of them really click.
就是，你知道，大家在尝试各种各样的东西。
Like, some of, you know, people are trying all sorts of stuff.
每个人都在搭建自己的个人系统。
Everybody's making these personal systems.
你问这里每个人是怎么用的，答案都不一样。
You ask everybody here what they do and everything's gonna be different.
然后会冒出一些共同的主题，我们就想，你知道吗？
And then, like, certain themes arise and we're like, you know what?
这应该成为应用里的一等公民体验。
That should be a first, a first class experience on the app.
就是我们应该把大家都在自己搭的这个东西，
Like we should take this thing that everybody seems to be setting up
直接做成开箱即用。
and just make that work.
我觉得 memory 差不多就是这种情况，我们这边很多人，
And I think memory is sort of in the shape where we've had a lot of people
其他公司也很多人，都在说，
and a lot of people at other companies too, are like, well,
我搭了一个 Obsidian 库或者 Notion 空间，
I set up an obsidian base or a notion area
我告诉它怎么帮我建这个记忆宫殿，怎么放东西。
and I tell it how to basically build my mind palace and how to put.
就像，我不知道是不是每个人，其实你不该需要这么做。
It's like, I don't know if everyone, like, you shouldn't have to do that.
应该有一个 memory 功能来帮你搞定这个，对吧？
Like there should be a memory feature that does that for you, right?
这种就比较通用。
That's pretty generic.
所以这算一类。
So that's, you know, that's one.
但也有另一些东西，是你工作里的流程，
But then there are other things like they're your process of your job
是那种确实该你自己去设置的。
and they're something that like, yeah, you should set that up.
但我觉得我们一直在筛选，哪些对
But I think this is we're constantly waiting through like what's working for
个人有用，什么该进产品，什么该留在个人层面？
individual people like what should what should enter the product versus stay?
就是，不，那只是你干活的方式，对吧？什么该成为一个基础能力？
Like, no, that's just how you do your job, right? What should become a primitive?
什么不该？
What shouldn't?
对，对。这就是。你前面说的
Yeah. Yeah. This is the. The taste
品位和判断力，就是用来决定这些的。
and judgment you spoke of earlier deciding these things.
我想稍微聊一下 browser use 这块，
I want to talk about this browser use piece a little bit
因为我觉得大家没意识到它有多强大，
because I think people don't realize how powerful this is
以及它能用来做什么。
and what it could be used for.
这让我想起，不知道你有没有看过 Dan Schipper 上播客那期，
Reminds me, I don't know if you watched when Dan Schipper was on the podcast,
他在 Every，他有个预测，说我们会开始用
he had this from every, he had this prediction that we're going to start using.
Codex 在里面运行我们的 SaaS 应用。对。
Codex to run our Saas apps inside it. Yeah.
所以不用去开 Chrome，我知道他每天都在 Slack 上找我要这类东西。
So instead of going in Chrome, I know he slacks me about this every day asking for stuff.
你觉得事情会朝这个方向发展吗，
Do you feel like this is where things go,
就是我们直接在 Codex 应用里工作，用 Notion、Linear，
where we're just working within the Codex app using notion and linear
还有 Salesforce，都在里面，agent 在旁边帮你？
and Salesforce inside with your agent kind of helping you along?
还是说你觉得那是另一个方向？
Or do you think that's kind of a different direction?
是啊，这一路其实非常有意思，
It's been, yeah, it's been really interesting
因为我们显然做过几次尝试。
because obviously we've had a few attempts at it.
浏览器形态的操作，对吧，还有 Operator、ChatGPT agent mode 和 Atlas。
Browser shaped activity, right, and operator and tragic agent mode and Atlas.
现在我们在桌面应用里有了应用内浏览器。
And now we have the in app browser inside of desktop app.
我们还能安装一个 Chrome 扩展。
We also have the the ability to install a Chrome extension
关于这个 app 怎么连接 Chrome，我们试过很多种形态
where the app connects to Chrome like we've had a lot of shapes of this
我觉得我们学到了很多不同的东西
and I think we've, we've Learned a lot of different things.
这里有很多可以发挥的空间，也有很多很枯燥的问题
There's, there's a lot of play. There's a lot of really boring things at play.
比如，我们最初发布这个 app 时，它是个 Electron app
Like, you know, we originally launched the app. It's an electron app.
app 内置浏览器能做的那些事情
The things that you can do with in app browsers in there.
其实有点糙、不太稳
It's it's like kind of janky.
所以我们的这个内置浏览器最初是为开发准备的
So we have the, the in app browser was for development.
是用来在开发时测试你的前端的
It was for testing your front end on development.
我们当时想，它其实没别的用途，各位，它就是
And we were like, it's not really for anything else, guys. Like it's,
一个开发者工具，对吧？
it's developer tool, right?
后来我们切换到了自己的 owl 技术栈，也就是支撑 Atlas 浏览器的那套
Then we, we switched over to our owl, owl stack, which had powered the Atlas browser.
所以现在有了多标签页，还有企业级安全
And so now, you know, multi tab and we've got enterprise security so
让你可以真正登录你所有的网站
that you can actually log into all your websites if you're, you know,
所以我们一直在迭代这块
so we've been iterating on this.
我觉得最难的问题一直是：这个浏览器应该长成什么样？
I think the tough thing has always been what should the shape of this browser be like?
它是只给 agent 用的吗？
Is this something that is only for the agent, right?
就是说你有 Chrome，你打开 Chrome，在 Chrome 里做你的事
That like you've got Chrome, you open Chrome, you, you know, do your thing in Chrome.
如果你让桌面应用去做，它就打开这个浏览器
If you ask the desktop app, it opens up this browser
它能很快地控制这个浏览器，没有 Playwright 之类的延迟
that it can control really quickly, doesn't have the latency of playwright whatever,
又或者，我们是不是想说这个 app 什么都能干
but that, you know, or are we trying to say this app is for everything
我们希望你把它当成一个
and like we want you to use this as a.
浏览器来用，而这些方案都有很多取舍，它不是特别
Browser and those have a lot of trade offs. It's not super, you know,
成熟的路子，对吧？
well traveled path, right?
比如大多数浏览器在最外层就是浏览器，它们有浏览器标签页
Like most browsers are browsers at the top level. They've got browser tabs.
这就带来了很多很枯燥但很繁琐的问题，比如键盘快捷键，对吧？
Um, this creates a lot of really boring but tedious problems like keyboard shortcuts, right?
我们的快捷键映射是照着 VS Code 还是 Chrome，还是我们自己的一套，还是照着
Are we trying to do key mapping to VS code or to Chrome or to our own thing or to
Linear 之类的？我们想要一种肌肉记忆
linear or like, you know, we want to have some sort of muscle memory
能延续下来，但又有这么多带着各自形态的东西
that carries over but got all these things that have shape like sub shapes of.
都是市面上不同产品的子形态，我们该怎么办？
Different products out on the market, what do we do?
这恰恰凸显了这个 app 有多难做
And this just highlights how extra challenging this app is
你得让它既能服务从没做过任何东西的人
where you have to allow it to work for somebody that's never built anything from,
从最基础的用户，一直到像 Peter 这样的高级用户
like, the more basic user to, like, power, like Peter.
是啊，用 OpenClaw 想拿它来写代码，我不确定我能不能说服 Peter
Yeah, hope and claw trying to code with it I I'm not convinced I'm gonna get Peter
来用这个 app，我觉得他可能是最后一个
to use the app I think he might be the last.
死守终端的人？好吧，但我会一直努力
Is it terminal holdout? Okay, but I'm gonna, I'm gonna keep trying.
好，让我，呃，往后退一步
Okay, let me, uh, let me zoom out for a moment
聊聊你要把这一切带向何方的大方向
and talk about kind of the big picture of where you're taking all this.
Codex 的愿景大概是什么？它会走向哪里？
What's the what's kind of the vision for, for Codex? Where does this go?
它会是什么样子？
What's it gonna look like?
比如一两年后、十年后，Codex 一开始是个 CLI，对吧？
You know, I don't know, a year or two, 10 years, we had Codex as a cli, right?
然后我们决定做这个 app
And then we decided to build this app and.
我们当时对这个 app 有点没把握，呃
You know, we were, we were a little uncertain about the app and, um,
但我们非常笃定它作为开发者工具起步能成为什么，对吧？
but had a lot of conviction and in what it could be as to start a developer tool, right?
它不会是一个 IDE
That, you know, and it wasn't gonna be an IDE,
它会是一个尺寸刚好的界面，有点像聊天机器人
it was gonna be this right sized surface where it was like sort of a chatbot,
但又不止于此
but it was more than that.
你能看到代码，但我们当时不会让你编辑代码
And you could see the code, but we weren't gonna let you edit the code.
在 OpenAI，一月、二月发生了一件很有意思的事
There's a really interesting thing that happened at OpenAI in January, in February,
那是在我们真正发布 Codex app 之前
and it was before we actually released the Codex app,
就是我们开始内部试用 Codex app
which is that we'd started to dogfood the Codex app.
我们发现，我们在内部逐渐收敛出了相当清晰的 PMF
And what we were finding, like we were converging on some pretty clear internal PMF
在工程和研究工作流上
on engineering, right, and research workflows.
他们非常兴奋，特别喜欢它
They were thrilled. They were loving it.
我们想，好，我们只要把质量标准拉上去
We were like, all right, we just gotta get the quality bar up
再把它发布给全世界
before we release it to the world.
我们确信这会成气候，但接着在公司里
We're convinced that this will be a thing, but then at the company,
我们又搞起了几条别的工作流，想说，嘿
we spun up a few other workflows to say, hey,
这个 Codex 项目在这些 coding agent 上确实找到了门道
like this Codex effort is onto something with these coding agents,
我们有来自市场、公关、财务的人
and we have people from marketing, from comms, from finance.
来自法务，几乎来自每个职能部门的人，都在用这个 Codex app
From legal, from basically every discipline who are using this Codex app,
尽管它对这些人其实是很不友好的，对吧？
even though it is actively hostile to these people, right?
它就像非要给他们看代码。
It is like trying to show them code.
它还想申请授权去运行 RG 之类的东西，
It's trying to ask for approval to run RG on the, you know,
它做的这一切，
it's like it's doing all of these things
对他们来说完全不是对的产品形态。
that are actively not the right product surface for them.
那我们为什么不把 Codex 加到我们其他的产品里呢，
So why don't we take our other surfaces and add Codex to them,
比如加到 ChatGPT 桌面应用，加到 Atlas 浏览器，对吧？
like let's add it to the ChatGPT desktop app, let's add it to the Atlas browser, right?
本质上就是把 Codex 的经验拿过来，让它更通用，
And let's essentially take the lessons of Codex and make it more general for,
做成一个通用的知识工作工具，对吧？
for a general knowledge work tool, right?
这些尝试进行了一段时间，然后出现了最烦人的问题，
And those efforts went for a little bit and the the most annoying problem happened,
就是没人愿意离开 Codex 应用，去用那些
which is nobody would leave the Codex app for the apps
号称是给其他用户群做的应用。
that were allegedly for these other personas.
我觉得这里面的教训就是，
And I think the lesson in all of this was just that,
所谓开发者工具和通用知识工作工具之争，
like the whole developer tool versus general knowledge work tool,
这里面有很多细微之处，不是非此即彼。
like there's a lot of nuance here that isn't just one or the other.
我觉得我们真的非常坚信这一点，
And I think we really, we believe really strongly in this and
而且确实，就像我们
that there are certainly, in the same way
说的，你岗位的平均状态就是你现在的岗位，
that we talk about the average of your role is like what your role is now,
在产品这边也是一样。
this is true on the product side too.
做 Excel 工作的人不想看到 Git 仓库信息。
People who are doing Excel work don't want to see Git repository information.
这个我们清楚。
We know that.
但我们也知道，从他们在做什么，能看出他们做的是哪类工作。
But we also know we can tell a lot from what they're doing about what kind of work they do.
我们可以从简单起步，按需要把产品做得更复杂，对吧？
And we can start simple, grow the product, complex as we feel is needed, right?
这不代表我们没有模式，对吧？
Doesn't mean we don't have modes, right?
你可能想要一些模式来整理你的东西，
You might want some modes for organizing your stuff
让你进入这个体验的方式变得清晰可读，对吧？
and to sort of be like legible about the the ways that you enter the experience, right?
但我们真的坚信，我们在这里做出来的东西，
But we really believe strongly that what we've built here is,
是承接那些非常深、垂直聚焦的场景的正确形态，对吧？
is the right shape to take, take on like really deep vertically focused things, right?
我们跟财务团队、科学团队紧密合作，
We work deeply with our finance team, with our team working on science team,
还有法务团队，对吧？
working on legal, right?
我们说，如果我们能构建出对的可扩展性原语，
And and we say like if we can build the right extensibility primitives.
放进对的通用模型里，那你就能用它做任何事。
In the right general model, then you can do anything with this.
那我们的挑战就是，你要怎么把它通用化呢？
And then our challenge is, well, how do you, you know, how do you generalize it?
但这又回到了，我们能做出的最好的桌面应用。
But this is kind of going back to, like, the best desktop app that we can build.
它到底是什么样子？
Like, what does that look like?
嗯，所以，Codex 是开发者工具，ChatGPT 呢，
Um, and so, you know, was Codex the developer tool, ChatGPT, like,
这一切要走向哪？
where's this going?
我们就是这么想的。
This is how we think about it.
你说的那点太有意思了，Codex 应用是如此……
It is so interesting, the point you made that the Codex app was so.
你们做得太成功了，让大家知道它的存在，
Like you did such a good job getting people to be aware it existed and
又那么好用、那么有趣，以至于大家都开始用它，
so good to use and fun to use that everyone's starting to use
而不是用 ChatGPT 应用。
that versus the chat GPT app.
所以方向显然是把它们合并起来，
So clearly the direction is combining them so
这样就不会制造这种混乱，我知道这是，
that you're not creating this confusion, which I know is, you know,
大家一直在讨论的，就是把它们整合到一起这个想法。
things people have been talking about, this idea of come bringing them together.
有人管它叫超级应用，真希望他们没这么说，
Somebody called it a super app and wish they hadn't said that
因为现在我每天都得听到"超级应用"这个词。
because now I have to hear about the super app all day every day.
我们会挺过去的。很好。
We'll get past it. Great.
好。
Okay.
但那是不是……我们就别叫它超级应用了，
But is that, is that kind of the not, let's not call it a super app,
但核心想法是，一个地方让大家做所有的事。
but the idea is like one place people go to do all the things.
这是大致的思路，还是说还没定？
Is that the general idea or TBD?
是的，我觉得我们在这里看到的是，它是一个很好的工作中枢。
Yeah, I think what we see here is that it's a great home base.
它是一个很好的地方，能追踪你需要做的
It's a great place to keep track of all of the things
跨不同产品的所有事情。
that you have to do across different surfaces.
其中有些事你全程都在这个应用里完成。
And some of those things you do all of it in the app.
有些事，这个应用会打开其他应用去完成，对吧？
Some of those things, the app opens other apps to, to do, right?
这个应用可以连接到 Excel，所以，是的，
The app can connect to Excel so that, you know, yes,
它在应用内部有一个电子表格编辑器。
it has a spreadsheet editor inside the app.
这对在 OpenAI 做融资财务建模的人来说够用吗
Is that good enough for people doing financial modeling at OpenAI for raising
花几十亿美元吗？
billions of dollars?
大概不会吧。
Like probably not.
所以这个应用会直接和你桌面上 Microsoft Excel 里的插件通信。
Um, and so the app talks directly to the add-in in Microsoft Excel on your desktop.
做完之后，你就可以关掉 Excel。
When it's done, you can close Excel, right?
所以它不只是说，嘿，
And so it's not just about, hey,
我们在屏幕上画一个方框，所有事情都得发生在那个框里。
we're drawing a rectangle on the screen and everything needs to happen in that rectangle.
而是它应该成为你的工作中枢，你在这里开始工作、结束工作，
It's this thing should be a home for you where you start work, you end work,
自动化工作，它会调用你需要用的一切。
you automate work, and it uses whatever you need to do.
有个很棒的故事，我们拍了一些视频，
There's a great story about, we had some videos
就是在这个房间里为 Codex 应用的首发拍的，
that we shot in this room for the original launch of the Codex app
我们的内部 DX 摄像师 Brent，
and our in-house DX videographer, Brent,
接手了剪辑这些视频的任务。
then was tasked with editing all these videos.
对吧？
Right?
他全程用 Codex 剪完了所有视频，这算是早期那种“哇”的时刻之一，
And he edited all the videos with Codex, which was one of the early like, whoa,
大家到底在用这东西干什么，对吧？
what are people doing with this thing, right?
而他决定开始用 Codex 的过程特别有意思。
And the process for why he decided to start using Codex was really interesting.
他一开始只是好奇 Codex 能不能剪视频。
He started just because he was curious if Codex could edit videos.
Codex 本身并不是视频剪辑工具。
And so Codex is not a video editor per se.
它里面没有任何那种界面。
It doesn't have any of that UI in it.
但它能理解他用的是 Premiere Pro。
But it was able to understand that he used Premiere Pro.
它能通过编辑那些文件来做一些剪辑，
It could do some edits by editing the files
也就是支撑 Premiere Pro 屏幕上内容的那些文件。
that were backing what was on screen in Premiere Pro.
但它没法做所有事情。
But it couldn't do everything.
于是 Codex 很自然地给自己造了一个扩展，
So naturally what Codex then did was built itself an extension
可以装进 Premiere Pro 里，然后它就能对它说，嘿，
that could be installed into Premiere Pro that it could then talk to and say, hey,
Premiere Pro 扩展，你能不能改一下 Premiere Pro 应用里的这个标记点？
Premiere Pro extension, can you please change this marker inside of the Premiere Pro app?
我们看到它这么干的时候真的挺震撼。这是个很棒的模式，对吧？
That was pretty nuts when we saw that happening. Um, it's a great model, right?
有很多专门做某件事的专业工具。
There are these like specialty tools that specialize in things.
所以我们想同时用 Codex，现在还有 ChatGPT 做两件事。
And so we're trying to do two things at once with Codex and with now with ChatGPT.
一是我们怎么能无缝地和你已经在用的这些工具交互，
One is how can we seamlessly interact with these tools that you're already using
我们不需要给你做一个更好的视频剪辑器，对吧？
and say like, we don't we don't need to build a better video editor for you, right?
但 Codex 和 ChatGPT 可以去用那个视频剪辑器，对吧？它可以去交互。
But like Codex and ChatGPT can use that video editor, right? It can interact again.
你可以把事情交给它，对吧？那我们该怎么做到这一点？
You can hand stuff off to it, right? So how can we do that?
通常是通过连接器、computer use，甚至像这个例子里的扩展。
And that's often through connectors or computer use or even extensions in this case.
对。
Right.
然后还有 Dan Shepherd 那种思路，就是，嘿，
And then there is, you know, Dan Shepherd's thing, which is, hey,
我有一些网页应用，你可以点来点去用，
I have these web apps that you can click around and use,
但我想能在 Codex 里打开它们，让 Codex 用它们做一些额外的事，对吧？
but I want to be able to open these in Codex and have Codex do extra stuff with it, right?
所以这算是两种几乎互为反向的模式，
And so those are kind of like two models that are almost inverse of each other
我们正在同时大力推进这两种。
that we're doing a lot with both at the same time.
这个 Premiere 的故事我觉得很有意思，
This premier story is interesting to me
因为它又一次说明，对这些 AI 任务可以更大胆一点。
because it's another example of just be more ambitious with these AI jobs.
你可能不知道，也许它们真能做到这件事。
Like you may not know, maybe they could do this thing.
几乎就是，去试，去试，看它能不能搞定。
It's almost just like, go try, go try, see if it figures it out.
我要带我们进入播客里的一个固定环节，我把它叫做 Fail Corner。
I'm gonna take us to a recurring corner on the podcast that I call Fail Corner.
问题是这样的，大家看到像你这样的人一路开挂、不断成长。
And so the question for you is, people see people like you just like killing it, just growing.
一切都在赢，Codex 做得这么好。
Everything's winning. Codex is doing so great.
这么疯狂的职业生涯，一切都在向右上方走。
This crazy career. Everything's up and to the right.
大家可能看不到那些没成的时候，还有那些
People may not see the times that things didn't work out and things
你发布过却以失败告终的东西。
that you launched that were failures.
所以这些故事对大家来说很重要，
And so these stories are really important for people to hear
让大家知道并不是一直都在赢。有没有一个故事？
that it's not all just win all the time. What's a story?
就是你职业生涯中失败过、但让你学到很重要东西的经历。
Of a time you failed in your career that taught you something really important.
听到别人这样描述我，还挺好笑的，
It's funny to hear that description played back at me and like,
这大概是我第一次不觉得自己在失败。
this is perhaps the first time I've I've not felt like I was failing.
我是说，我做过很长时间的创业公司创始人。
I mean, I was a startup founder for a long time.
最后基本上是把公司拆开卖掉了。
I ended up selling the company for parts essentially, right.
那真是耗了好几年，一路苦熬。
And it was just, it was years, it was a slog.
那是监管很重的领域，整件事感觉就像持续不断的失败。
It was heavily regulated spaces, the whole thing felt like a constant failure.
后来我去了另一家创业公司，我们想做一些 AI 工具，
Um, I went to this other startup and we were trying to do some AI tools and
而且这还是个相当封闭、监管很严的行业
and this also like pretty lockdown regulated industry and
感觉就是一次又一次地尝试，然后失败
that felt like just time after time of trying things and it not working.
所以对我来说，我其实失败了很多次
So to me it's been like, oh, I've failed actually quite a lot.
你知道，有时候就是某个时间点
And, you know, sometimes it's just a point in time
各种东西刚好对上了，比如技能、热情、市场时机
where things line up like skill set, passion point in the market lineup.
我们做这个项目，就是把我们从
We, with this, you know, with this project to bring what we've learned with the
Codex 应用学到的东西和 ChatGPT 结合起来，其中经历了
Codex app and marry it with ChatGPT, there have been,
我都不知道有多少次小失败，我们会觉得
I don't know how many micro failures on this where we're like.
这就是它该有的样子，然后扔到 Slack 里
This is the shape it should look like and then throw that in Slack
然后就有个两千条消息的帖子，说我们有多蠢
and there's like a 2,000 message thread about how stupid we are.
就是这样。这正是我喜欢 OpenAI 的地方
And it's like that. This is the thing I love about OpenAI's.
大家会直接告诉你，对吧？
People will just tell us that, right?
没有，呃，没有任何遮遮掩掩
There's, there's no, uh, there's no holding back on like
当我们在内部产品上失败时
when we fail with product things internally,
这也是为什么对外的产品能做得很好，因为它经历了
it's why the external product has been pretty great is cuz it goes through these
这些循环，两千条消息
cycles of life, 2000.
挺糟的。我失败了，大概
The sucks. I failed for like, I don't know,
在走到今天之前，失败了十到十五年
somewhere between 10 and 15 years before getting to this point.
所以我每天还是很惊讶事情居然进展顺利
So I'm still surprised every day that things are going well.
我心里清楚
And I know it.
我觉得这一点对大家来说真的很重要
I like but I think this is really important for people to hear
你可以有很多事情都失败
that you can have a lot of things not work out
然后事情开始变得特别顺，关键就是坚持下去
and then things start to work out super well and it's just keep going
不断学习
and keep learning.
我想这是个教训。好，说到这里，我们
I imagine is, is a lesson. Well, with that, we're, uh,
我们进入非常激动人心的闪电问答环节
we reached our very exciting Lightning round.
我有五个问题问你。准备好了吗？开始
I've got five questions for you. Are you ready? Here we go.
呃，有哪两三本书是你最常推荐给别人的？
Uh, what are two or three books that you find yourself recommending most to other people?
你看，我现在当爸爸了，孩子还小
See, man, I'm, I'm a parent now. I'm a parent of young kids.
所以我，我不知道，有一本叫 Gruffalo（咕噜牛）我读给孩子听
So I, I'm like, I don't know, there's one called the Gruffalo I read to my kids.
我的天，我们家孩子最近就迷上了 Gruffalo。对，我们有个
I, oh, my God, our kid just got obsessed with the Gruffalo. Yes. Uh, we have like a.
睡前流程表？对。现在就是睡衣、刷牙、看书
A bedtime chart? Yeah. And now it's like pajamas, brush, teeth, books,
Gruffalo、盖毯子
Gruffalo on blanky.
对对。太好了。所以我现在读的其他书也是那种风格
Yeah, yeah. It's so good. So other books I'm reading right now are like that style.
我觉得，其实 Gruffalo 还挺不错的。是啊
I'm like, actually, the Gruffalo is not a terrible one. No,
我感觉里面还有些道理
I feel like there's some lessons.
好可爱。对。不过每本童书都在讲死亡
So sweet. Yeah. Although every kids book is about death,
比如谁吃谁，谁杀谁
like someone's eating someone, someone's killing.
总有坏事，比如谋杀。对。还有破坏
There's always, like, bad, like murder. Yeah. And. And destruction.
孩子喜欢暴力，哪怕他们不觉得那是暴力
Kids like violence even when it doesn't feel like violence to them.
就是那些词，它营造出一种故事张力和兴奋感
That like the words that this like, it creates like an arc and excitement.
对对。好，很好的选择，Gruffalo。我现在积压了一堆书
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Great choice, Gruffalo. I currently have a book backlog.
我，我得把它们全读完。还有其他孩子喜欢的
I, I need like, I need to read all of them. Any other children's books that,
童书吗？
that your kid likes?
好，其实，呃，我对童书还挺懂的
Okay, so, yes, actually, um, I am well versed on children's base.
我最喜欢的一本童书是很老的一本
My favorite children's book ever is a very old one
叫 The Big Orange Spot，大概是这个名字
and it's called The Big Orange Spot or something along those lines.
查一下吧。特别好。去买一本
Look it up. It's great. Go get it.
如果你讨厌 HOA（业主委员会），去买一本
If you hate HOAs, go get it.
它讲的是一个人，Mr Plumbean（普拉宾先生）
It's about this guy, Mr Plumbing,
他住在一条所有房子都一模一样的街上
who lives on a street where all the houses are the same.
街道非常整齐
It's very neat street.
有一天，一只鸟把一大罐橙色油漆掉在他房子上，他就说
And then one day a bird drops a large can of orange paint on his house and he says,
去他的，我要放手一搏
eff, eff it, like, I'm going all in.
于是他去店里买了油漆、吊床
So he goes to the store, he gets paint, hammocks,
短吻鳄，然后把房子彻底翻新了
alligators and he's like totally redos his house.
邻居们都炸锅了，对吧？就是那种 HOA
And the neighbors, like, they're up in arms, right? Like, you know, HOA,
房产价值之类的
property value, whatever, whatever.
呃，它其实不是讲 HOA 的，但我特别反对 HOA。这书真的很酷
Um, it's not about HOAs, but I very anti HOA person. It's just really cool.
然后邻居们一个接一个去找他聊，呃
And then like one by one, the neighbors go talk to him, have, uh,
他们把它叫做"lemonade"，
what they refer to as lemonade,
但那是非常有说服力的"lemonade"
but like it's very convincing lemonade
因为他们一个接一个开始改造自己的房子，有个人还做了艘船
because one by one they all start redoing their house like one guy does like a boat,
对吧？我觉得那是本好书。
right? I think that's a good book. I think.
人们尤其是新手，都该读一读。
People need to read this when they're especially, you know, newbies.
我从中听到的是主动性、能动性。
What I hear from this is agency agents.
没错。你可以直接去做事。就去做。
Exactly. You can just do things. Just do things.
很棒。好，我们继续。
Amazing. Okay, we'll keep going.
如果你最近有空，最喜欢的电影或剧是什么？
Favorite recent movie or TV show you really enjoyed if you've had any time.
The Magic School Bus 又在 Netflix 上线了。是部新动画。
So The Magic School Bus is back on Netflix. It's. It's a new animated.
里面有 Kate McKinnon，因为 Miss Frizzle 现在是 Professor Frizzle，她
It's got Kate Mckinnon because Miss Frizzle is now Professor Frizzle and she's,
你懂的，还在，但不是主角 Frizzle 了。
you know, around, but she's not the main frizzle.
现在 Kate McKinnon 演主角 Miss Frizzle。是的，
Now. Kate Mckinnon plays the main Miss Frizzle. It's, yeah,
我一直挺喜欢 The Magic School Bus 的。
I always liked the Magic School Bus.
它回来了。不过我自己还没看过。
It's back. I've never seen of her used it personally.
我没时间看电影，所以我会看那种一小时长的 Netflix，
Like I don't have time for movies so what I do is watch hour long Netflix,
一集接一集地看。
Netflix things back to back.
你知道有人会说，哦，我坐不住，
You know that thing that people do like, oh, I couldn't sit,
我没法坐下来看完一整部电影
I couldn't sit down and watch a whole movie
但可以一直看一小时一集的剧。
and then like watch hour long episodes and keep.
是的，我会这样。那种方式有点让人上瘾。
Yeah, I do some. There's something addicting about that way.
你最近发现并很喜欢的产品是什么？
Favorite product you've recently discovered that you really love?
这答案糟透了？我感觉每天都在重新发现我们自己的产品。
What was a terrible answer? I feel like I'm discovering our product every day.
很好。
Beautiful.
我觉得 Linear 做得很棒。
That's so I think linear does a great job.
在这之前，Linear 至少是我最喜欢的软件产品。
Like linear until until this linear was like my favorite at least software product.
你们就用它来做规划吗？理论上是。
Is that what you guys use to to plan and. Well, in theory.
你有没有最喜欢的人生格言
Do you have a favorite life motto
在工作或生活中会反复想起的？
that you find yourself coming back to in work or in life?
我想问每个跟我共事的人这个问题，因为我
I want to ask everyone who works with me this, because I, I, I,
我觉得自己不是爱讲格言的人，但别人会告诉我一些我常挂嘴边的话。
I feel like I'm not a moto person and then people tell me stuff I say all the time.
是啊，比如我们之前聊天的时候，
Yeah, like when we were chatting ahead of this,
有很多小金句让我印象深刻
there's so many little nuggets that stood out to me
我都融进了这次对话里。
that I've integrated into this chat.
所以我完全理解。好，最后一个问题。
So I I totally hear that. Okay, last question.
你当过 PM，当过设计师，
You've been a PM, you've been a designer,
也当过工程师，这三个角色里哪个最难？
you've been an engineer which is the toughest role of the three?
哪个最难？想挑起战争吗？
Which is like the hardest? Start a war?
是的。我也不知道。
Yes. I don't know.
我觉得它们都很不一样。
I think they're all very different.
让一个人觉得难的东西，对另一个人可能很容易。
And the things that make it tough for one person make it easy for others.
这里面有很多。有太多不同的看法。
There's a lot. There's so much, so many takes on this.
还有这个三角组合，它会怎么演变？
And like this triad, what's gonna happen with this triad?
比如设计师完蛋了？设计师该写代码吗？PM 完了？工程师呢？
Like, designers are done or like should designers code our PMS cooked like our engine?
呃，我们是不是不再需要工程师了
Uh, do we not need engineers any more
因为 PM 要写所有代码，或者设计师现在要做 PM
because PMS are gonna write all the code or designer's gonna PM now
好像每个人都完了，又好像每个人都翻身了，我也说不清，
and like everybody's cooked and everybody's so back and I don't know,
感觉有一种融合在发生。
like there's some convergence.
出现了一种流动性，我觉得很清新、很棒，
There's some fluidity that is being introduced that I think is refreshing and great,
尤其对那些有能动性、想直接把事情做成的人来说
especially for people with agency that want to be able to just like do the thing
想把该做的事做成的人。
that needs to get done.
呃，同时，就像我们聊过的，
Um, and at the same time, like we talked about,
有些东西是不该消失的，
there are some things that shouldn't go away,
但我觉得人们应该找到值得投入的事
but I think people should find the stuff that's worth working on
然后去弄清楚在这些事上该怎么做。
and go figure out what to do on those things.
这个结尾太棒了。Andrew，非常感谢你来到这里。
That is a beautiful way to end it. Andrew, thank you so much for being here.
谢谢。
Thank you.
大家再见。
Bye, everyone.
非常感谢你的收听。
Thank you so much for listening.
如果你觉得有价值，可以在 Apple Podcasts 上订阅本节目，
If you found this valuable, you can subscribe to the show on Apple Podcasts,
Spotify 或你喜欢的播客应用。
Spotify or your favorite podcast app.
也请考虑给我们打个分或留个评论，
Also, please consider giving us a rating or leaving a review as
这真的能帮到其他听众发现这个播客。
that really helps other listeners find the podcast.
你可以在 Lenny'spodcast.com 找到所有往期节目或了解更多。
You can find all past episodes or learn more about the show at Lenny's podcast.com.
下期节目见。
See you in the next episode.
我很喜欢你在 Premiere Pro 里讲的那件事。对，很酷。我其实也用过。
I love that thing about Brent in the Premiere Pro. Yeah, that's cool. I've actually used.
哦，剪辑，也能剪。基本上就是一些简单的活儿，比如，
Oh, edit, edits as well. Basically simple stuff like, oh,
能不能把这段剪成三个停顿？
could you just cut this into the three breaks?
你知道的，比如对话中有停顿，
You know, like, if there's a pause in conversation, like,
我一编码它就能理解。
the second I encode it understands it.
基本上，我们觉得每份工作都是从这样的故事开始的，
Basically, every job we feel like starts with a story like this,
就是产品本来不是为它设计的，
which is the product's not designed for it,
但它有点像一个能写代码的空白聊天机器人，所以什么都能做。
but it's sort of a blank chatbot that can write code so can do everything.
但具体是什么呢？
But like what?
它能做的有用的事情是什么，对吧？
What are the useful things for it to do, right?
我是说，人们只要对手上的项目有好奇心，他们得，
I mean, people just have to have curiosity about the project they, they have to,
你懂的，带着一个明确的目标，把 Codex 当作平台，
you know, have it in an intentional outcome and use Codex as the platform for
用它去看看会发生什么。
that just to see what happens.
你知道，完全没有风险，对吧？就几个 token。几个 token 而已。
You know, there's no risk at all, right? Just a few tokens. Few tokens.
当然，如果你在 OpenAI 工作，这方面的风险就更小了。
But of course, if you're working for OpenAI, there's less risks on that regard.
对。你问过其中一个，问什么来着？其实是问了很多人，
Yeah. You asked, um, one of them like what? Or a lot of them actually,
就是哪些技能重要？
like what skills are important?
对。
Yeah.
然后你也聊过那种超厉害的应届生
It's like, then, then you've also had conversations about like the cracked new grad
对比……对，我不知道
versus the, yeah, like, I don't know
你是不是死守着你现在的这套流程。
if you're married to the exact process you have right now.
那种，我不知道能给什么建议，但如果只有一条，
Like that, I don't know what advice to ever give, but if there's one piece,
那就是不要死守你现在的具体流程。
it's like do not get married to your exact process.
要守住的是那些只有你能交付的成果，
Get married to like the outcomes that you were uniquely able to deliver
然后去做一些事，比如改变你的流程，尝试新东西，你就一直，
and then do things like change your process to try things like you just keep,
你会说，我最懂 Figma 的自动布局，对吧，
you're like, I'm the best at understanding Figma auto layout, like, right,
你这是在干嘛？
what are you doing?
对吧？因为 AI 在那方面会做得更好。对，
Right? Cause AI is gonna be better at that. Yeah,
所以你就不断抛出有趣的东西，保持住。
so you just keep spouting interesting things, keep it in.
用 AI 想要做出成绩，所需要的自我认知程度真的很夸张。
It's crazy the level of self awareness that's required to like be successful with AI.
确实。对。
It is. Yeah.
这也是为什么我很怕说，
It's also why I'm nervous to ever say, like,
事情就该是这样，因为我会想到，我父母是很开明的
this is how something's gonna be cause I think about like my parents are open minded
人。他们也很投入自己的事业。但就是，
people. They are into their careers. But just like.
在这里管用的东西，就是不会，不会对所有人都管用。
The stuff that works here is just not gonna, it's not gonna work with everybody.
这话没什么好听的说法，你懂的，
There's no nice way of saying that, you know,
但在这里的人都是自我筛选出来的，就是那种，哦，
but like the people who are here are self selecting for like, oh,
我是那种自己就能琢磨出下一步该做什么的人，
I'm somebody who just figures out the next thing to do and
而这就不像……大多数人不会是早期采用者。
that's just not like most of the population will not be an early adopter of.
对新事物。
Things.
还有就是，总得不断重新学东西，其实挺让人扫兴的。
And there's also just like, it's kind of like us a bummer to have to relearn things all the time.
对。你知道，就是那种，妈的又要学新东西了。
Yeah. You know, it's like God damn it to learn a new thing again.
对，我讨厌重复。这是我个人的特点。
Yeah, like I, I hate repetition. This is like a me thing.
我不……这也是为什么我从来都不是最擅长做媒体的人，因为我
Like I don't, this is why I'm like not ever the best media person either cause I
就是，我讨厌重复自己。
just like, I hate repeating myself.
太对了。当你讨厌重复自己时，做创始人就很痛苦，因为你，
Perfect. Um, sucks to be a founder when you hate repeating yourself cause you,
你基本上得当那个首席复读机。
you'd like have to repeater in chief.
嗯，所以对我来说，我会想，
Um, and so like to me, I'm like,
如果我能每天用不同的方式来做我的工作。
if I can come in and do my job at a different way every day.
那我很喜欢。但那不是……
Love it. But like, that's not.
你为自己的工作找到了产品市场契合点。是的。对。
You found product market fit for your job. Yes. Yeah.
不，就是这样，我基本没法谈条件，因为我会想，嗯，
No, that's how it, that's, I like can't negotiate because I'm like, well,
我不想要别的工作。太棒了，兄弟。好，谢谢你。
I don't want other jobs. Amazing man. Well, thank you.